<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first part of the pleasant and princely history of the gentle-craft a discourse containing many matters of delight very plesant to read, shewing what famous men have been shoo-makers in time past in this land, with their worthy deeds and great hospitality / set forth with pictures and variety of wit and mirth, declaring the cause why it is called the gentle-craft, and also how the proverb first grew, A shoo-makers son is a prince born, [by] T.D.</title>
            <author>Deloney, Thomas, 1543?-1600.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37504</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13326652</idno>
  <idno type="VID">99084</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240877982</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D944</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33441</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13326652</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37504)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99084)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1548:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first part of the pleasant and princely history of the gentle-craft a discourse containing many matters of delight very plesant to read, shewing what famous men have been shoo-makers in time past in this land, with their worthy deeds and great hospitality / set forth with pictures and variety of wit and mirth, declaring the cause why it is called the gentle-craft, and also how the proverb first grew, A shoo-makers son is a prince born, [by] T.D.</title>
                  <author>Deloney, Thomas, 1543?-1600.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 50, [1] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.M. for William Thackery ..,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99084:1"/>
            <p>THE FIRST PART OF THE Pleasant and Princely HISTORY OF THE GENTLE-CRAFT. A DISCOURSE Containing many matters of Delight: Very Pleasant to Read. SHEWING What Famous Men have been <hi>SHOO-MAKERS</hi> in time past in this Land, with their Worthy Deeds, and great Hospitality. Set forth with Pictures, and Variety of Wit and Mirth. Declaring the cause why it is called the GENTLE-CRAFT: And also how the PROVERB first grew:
<q>
                  <hi>A SHOO-MAKERS Son is a Prince Born.</hi>
                  <bibl>T. D.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>With gentleness judge you,</l>
               <l>At nothing here grudge you,</l>
               <l>The merry Shoo-makers delight in good sport:</l>
               <l>What here is presented,</l>
               <l>Be therewith contented,</l>
               <l>And as you do like it, so give your Report.</l>
            </lg>
            <q>
               <hi>Haud curo invidiam.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. M.</hi> for <hi>William Thackery</hi> in <hi>Duck-Lane,</hi> near <hi>West-Smith-field,</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:99084:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of saints Crispinian and Crispin</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <label>Crispianus</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Crispin</label>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Honour and many Victories, do Crown,</l>
               <l>The Name of <hi>Crispianus</hi> with Renown:</l>
               <l>Whilst <hi>Crispine</hi> a new Conqueror doth prove,</l>
               <l>And wins at home a Royal LADIES Love.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:99084:2"/>
            <head>The History of the GENTLE-CRAFT</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of lady attended by young shoemaker</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>A <hi>Gentle Craft</hi> that hath the Art,</l>
               <l>To steal soon into a LADIES Heart;</l>
               <l>Here you may see, what Youth and Love can do,</l>
               <l>The Crown doth stoop to th'Maker of a Shooe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99084:3"/>
            <head>To all the good YEOMEN OF THE Gentle-Craft.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>YOU that the Gentle Craft profess,</l>
               <l>List to my Words both more and less,</l>
               <l>And I shall tell you many things</l>
               <l>Of worthy and renowned Kings:</l>
               <l>And divers Lords and Knights also,</l>
               <l>That were Shoomakers long ago:</l>
               <l>Some of them in their distress,</l>
               <l>Delighted in this business:</l>
               <l>And some for whom great wait was laid</l>
               <l>Did save their lives by this same Trade:</l>
               <l>Other some, in sport and game,</l>
               <l>Delighted much to learn the same:</l>
               <l>No other Trade in all the Land,</l>
               <l>They thought so fit unto their hand;</l>
               <l>For evermore they still did find,</l>
               <l>That shoomakers bore a gallant mind:</l>
               <l>Men they were of high conceit,</l>
               <l>The which wrought many a merry feat:</l>
               <l>Stout of Courage were they still,</l>
               <l>And in their Weapons had great skill:</l>
               <l>Travellers by Sea and Land,</l>
               <l>Each Countryguise to understand.</l>
               <l>Wrong they wrought not any man,</l>
               <l>With reason all things did they scan;</l>
               <l>Good houses kept they evermore,</l>
               <l>Relieving both the Sick and Poor.</l>
               <l>in Law no money would they spend,</l>
               <l>Their quarrels friendly would they end.</l>
               <l>No malice did they bear to any,</l>
               <l>But shew'd great favor unto many,</l>
               <l>Offences they would soon forgive,</l>
               <l>They would not in contention live,</l>
               <l>Thus in joy they spent their days,</l>
               <l>With pleasant Songs and Roundelais;</l>
               <l>And God did bless them with content,</l>
               <l>Sufficient for them he sent;</l>
               <l>And never yet did any know,</l>
               <l>A shoomaker a begging go:</l>
               <l>Kind are they one to another,</l>
               <l>Using each stranger as his Brother.</l>
               <l>Thus lived shoomakers of Old,</l>
               <l>As antient Writers have it told;</l>
               <l>And thus shoomakers still would be,</l>
               <l>So Fame from them shall never flee.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="advice">
            <pb facs="tcp:99084:3"/>
            <head>The Old <hi>SHOO-MAKERS</hi> Advice to his Son, Being the Downfal of ALEWIVES.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>YOung Man, that now art in thy prime, beware of Drunkenness,</l>
               <l>Thy Father hath mispent his time in that same fowl Excess:</l>
               <l>Which made me for to write to thee, the Ale-house to refrain,</l>
               <l>Because it hath quite ruin'd me, spending my time in vain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Wall-nut is a pleasant Fruit, and hath a bitter Skin,</l>
               <l>If with the Ale-wife thou dispute, she'l make thy purse but thin:</l>
               <l>Thy mony must maintain her Pride, and by her Cobweb-Lawn,</l>
               <l>Whilst thou for Bear and Ale beside, dost lay thy Cloak to pawn.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Good Counclishe will seem to give, but if thou stay away,</l>
               <l>This woman knows not how to live, her Trade will soon decay.</l>
               <l>Thou work'st for her both Day and Night, and all to pay thy score:</l>
               <l>She loves to see thee in her sight, and all to keep thee poor.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'l make a very Rogue of thee i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou by her be rul'd,</l>
               <l>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'st thou not better to go free, than be by her thus fool'd.</l>
               <l>When thou goest home to wig to wag, praising thy own good carriage,</l>
               <l>Thy cloaths no better than a Rag, O this will spoyl thy Marriage</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She evermore will thee perswade never to take a Wife,</l>
               <l>For why she thinks 'twill spoyl her Trade, and be the cause of strife:</l>
               <l>If thou be ne'r so much in hast, shee'l cause thee for to stay,</l>
               <l>The Cubbard then must be unca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d, tush, what will you away?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She'l bring a piece of powder'd beef, or a Virginy Trout,</l>
               <l>O shee's a very loving thief, shee'l find thy money out.</l>
               <l>Her Lettice shews as thou maist see, she sells both Ale and Beer,</l>
               <l>But O beware, be rul'd by me, buy not her ware too dear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For she will hold some folks in talk, both <hi>Ieffery, Iames and Iohn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then with a double forked chalk, shee'l score two pots for one:</l>
               <l>I'le tell you of a story good, ye Drunkards men your lives:</l>
               <l>If it be rightly understood, you you'l never love ale Wives.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Two Drunkards lov'd each other well, and both liv'd in one house,</l>
               <l>The thing is true which I will tell, the best not worth a louse:</l>
               <l>One of them dy'd, and left his Cloak and Sute unto the other:</l>
               <l>They spent their coyn in drink and smoak, and ruined each other,</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:99084:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But mark the Ale-wives cruelty, she claim'd all for her own;</l>
               <l>Because the man that then did dye, was in her debt, 'twas known.</l>
               <l>Then have a care my honest Lad, if thou dye ne'r so poor,</l>
               <l>If any thing be to be had, 'tis that must pay thy score.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O then live but a civil life, and scrape this Dragon fell,</l>
               <l>Thou may'st prevent much drunken strife, and then thou shalt do well.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Crispine</hi> and <hi>Crispianus</hi> stout, were proper men and tall:</l>
               <l>But if thou beat this Dragon out, thou dost more than them all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For he that can himself subdue, and bridle his own will,</l>
               <l>O he doth more than if he slew, and did ten Dragons kill.</l>
               <l>Gentlemen of the Gentle-Craft, I wish so well to all,</l>
               <l>Although you drink your mornings draught, let none procure your fall:</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>To all Courteous Readers, Health.</head>
            <p>HOw St. <hi>Hugh</hi> was Son unto the Renowned King of <hi>Powis,</hi> a Noble <hi>Brittain</hi> born, who in the prime of his Years, loved the fair Virgin <hi>Winifred:</hi> who was the only Daughter of <hi>Donwallo:</hi> which was the last King that Reigned in <hi>Tegina,</hi> which is now called <hi>Flintshire:</hi> But she refusing all offers of Love, was only pleased with a Religious life. Her Father was sent to <hi>Rome,</hi> and dyed, whose Lady left her life long before. This Virgin therefore, forsook her Fathers Princely Pallace in <hi>Pant Varre,</hi> and made her whole abiding in the most sweet and pleasant Valley of <hi>Sichnaunt,</hi> and lived there solitarily, and careless of all company or comfort: It chanced that in summers heat, this fair Virgin being distressed for want of drink, and not knowing where to get any, there sprang up sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly a Crystal stream of most pleasant water out of the hard ground, whereof this Virgin did dayly drink; unto the which God himself gave so great a vertue, that many people hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been washed therein, were healed of divers and sundry infirmities, wherewith they were born. Moreover, round about this VVell where this Virgin did use to walk, did grow a kind of Moss, which is of a most sweet savour, and the colour thereof is as fresh in VVinter as in Summer, so that lying thereon you would suppose your self to be on a bed of Down, perfumed with most precious Odours. And what of all this? Marry, read this Book and you shall know: but read nothing except you read all. And why so? Because the beginning shews not the middle, and the middle shews not the latter end.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>And so Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99084:4"/>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The Pleasant History of Sir <hi>Hugh,</hi> and first of all his constant Love to the fair Virgin <hi>Winifred.</hi>
               </head>
               <figure/>
               <p>COnquering and most imperious Love, having seized on the heart of young Sir <hi>Hugh;</hi> all his wits were set on work, how to compass the Love of the fair Virgin <hi>Winifred,</hi> whose disdain was the chief cause of his care, having received many infinite sorrows for her sake. But as a stream of water being stopt, over-floweth the bank; so smothered desire doth burst out into a great flame of fire, which made the Male-contented lover to seek some means to appease the strife of his contentious thoughts, whereupon he began to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage himself: Tush <hi>Hugh,</hi> let not a few froward words of a Women dismay thee, for they love to be intreated, and delight to be Wooed, though they would make the world believe otherwise, for their denials proceed more of niceness than niggardli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, refusing that they would fainest have. What if sometimes <hi>Winifred</hi> frown on thee, yet her favour may exceed her frowardness. The Sun is sometimes over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cast with Clouds, so that her brightness is not seen: In wars, the sorer the fight is, the greater is the glory of the victory; and the harder a woman is to be won, the sweeter is her love when it is obtained: Wherefore I'le once again try my fortune, and see what success my suit shall find: On this resolution Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> returned to <hi>Winifred,</hi> gréeting her thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now fair Lady, having slept away the Remembrance of your sharp answers, I come again in a new conceit to renew an old suit, and to see if the chang of the day will yield a change of dolours.</hi> Truly Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> (<abbr>qd</abbr> she) if with the change of the day you have changed your opinion, your dolour will be driven away well enough: but as touching your suit, it shall be needless to repeat it, because I am not willing to prefer it. <hi>Stay there</hi> (<abbr>qd</abbr> Sir <hi>Hugh</hi>) <hi>I will prefer it; so that you will accept it.</hi> Now. <abbr>qd</abbr> she, I will accept it, if you will prefer it, in sending it back to the place from whence it did procéed; and <hi>I</hi> would to God, <hi>I</hi> could send you away as soon as your suit. <hi>Why then be like I am not welcome,</hi> said Sir <hi>Hugh:</hi> Yes, <abbr>qd</abbr> she, as welcome to meas a storm
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99084:5"/> to a distressed Marriner: I muse greatly that reason will not rule you, nor words win you from your wilfulness; if you were as weary to wooe, as I am weary to hear you, I am perswaded that long since you would have ceased your vain suit: You think by these perswasions to turn my opinion; but as well you may think that you may quench fire with oyl; therefore I pray you good Sir <hi>Hugh,</hi> be not so tedious to me, nor troublesome to your self.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Come, come,</hi> quoth he, <hi>all this will not serve your turn: ponder with thy self</hi> Wini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred, <hi>that thou art fair, O that thou wert as favourable: thy beauty hath bound me to be thy servant, and never cease till I see another obtain thee, or my self be possessed of my hearts content: Thou art a Kings daughter, and I a Princes Son; stain not the glory of true Nobility with the foul sin of obstinacy, but be thou as kind as thou art courtly, and gentle as thou art noble, and then shall our strife soon end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Winifred</hi> perceiving that the farther off she was to grant love, the more eager he was to desire it, shifted him off thus: Sir, although your over-hastiness drive me into the greatest doubtfulness, yet let me intreat you, if you love me, to give me one months respite to consider on this matter, and it may be, that upon my better deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration, it shall be pleasing unto you, and not at all discontenting me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fair love,</hi> quoth he, <hi>far be it from my heart to deny so kind a request, I am content to stay a month from thy sight, were i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> two or three, upon condition that thou wouldst then grant me thy good will; three months, although it be very long, yet it will come at last, and I could be content for that time to be dead for thy sake, insomuch, that my life might be renewed by thy love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay (<abbr>qd</abbr>
                  <hi>Winifred</hi>) stay three months and stay for ever: By this a Maid may see how ready men are upon a light occasion to take long days, whose loves are like a Fern-bush, soon set on fire, and soon consumed; and seeing it is so, in faith Sir <hi>Hugh,</hi> I do mean to try you before I trust you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pardon me fair</hi> Winifred, said Sir <hi>Hugh, if my tongue doth out-stip my wit, in truth I spake but to please thee, though to displease my self: but I pray thee, let it not be three hours, nor three quarters of an hour, if thou wilt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, nay (quoth she) your first words shall stand; after three months come to me again, and then you shall know my mind to the full, and so good Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> be gone: but if I do ever hear from thee, or see thee betwixt this time and the time prefixed. I will for ever hereafter blot out thy name out of my book of remembrance, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yield thee that courtesie, which thou at this time so earnestly intreatest for.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> upon these words departed betwixt hope and dread, much like a man committing a trespass, that stayes for the sentence of Life and Death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O unhappy man,</hi> quoth he, <hi>how hath my over-slippery tongue lengthened the time of my sorrow? she of her self most courteously requested of me but one months stay, and I most willingly and undiscreetly added thereto eight weeks more of misery. Much like the Hand, that having a knife given him to pare his Nails, did therewith murder him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self. Now I could wish that the Sun had Eagles wings, swiftly to flye through the fair Firmament, and finish six days in one days time.</hi> With that he began to count the days and hours that were in three months, falling (in a manner) to a despair with himself when he found them so many in number: and therewithal melancholly and sadly, he went to his Fathers house, where his Brother <hi>Griffith</hi> found by his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the perfect map of a pensive Lover: whereupon he said unto him:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why, how now Brother? hath fair</hi> Winifreds <hi>beauty so greatly wounded you, as you cannot speak a merry word to your friend, but sit in a corner as if you were tongue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse like a stock? Tush brother, women are like shadows, for the more a man follows
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99084:5"/> them, the faster they run away; but let a man turn his course, and then they will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently follow him. What man, pluck up a good heart, for there are more women now, than lived in the time of old Father</hi> Adam.</p>
               <p>O, said <hi>Hugh,</hi> were there ten thousand times more than there are now, what were that to me, if <hi>Winifred</hi> be unkind? Yet is she the Oyl that still maintains the lamp of my light, and without her there is nothing comfortable to my sight.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then</hi> (replyed <hi>Griffith</hi>) <hi>you are as much troubled in love, as a Goat in an Ague, and as blind as a flye in</hi> October, <hi>that will stand still while a man cuts off his head; Come, go a hunting with me, that will drive away your over-fond conceits, and you shall see that these three months will come upon you, as a quarter-day upon a poor man, that hath never a penny ready towards the payment of his Rent.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. How beautiful <hi>Winifred,</hi> being over much superstitious, forsook her Fathers wealth, and lived poorly by a springing fountain, from whence no man could get her to go; which Spring to this day is called <hi>Winifreds</hi> well.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <hi>WInifred,</hi> who had but of late years, with her own father, received the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Faith, because so superstitious, that she thought the wealth of the world for ever would have been an heavy burthen for her soul, and have drawn her mind from the love of her Master; wherefore, forsaking all manner of earthly pomp, she lived a long time very poorly, hard by the side of a most pleasant springing Well: from which place neither her friends by intreaty, nor her foes by violence could bring her: which Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> hearing, he went thither immediately after unto her, which was the time limited by them both, and finding her mind altogether altered, he wondred not a little what she meant. And when he approached near unto the place where she sat suited in simple attire, he saluted her with these words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All health to fair</hi> Winifred; <hi>I trust my dear, that now the Destinies have yielded a convenient opportunity for me to finish my long begun suit, with the end of my former sorrows. Long and tedious hath the winter of my woes been, which with nipping care hath blasted the beauty of my youthful delight, which is like never again to flourish, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the bright Sun-shine of thy favour do renew the same: therefore fair love remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy promise made unto me, and put me no mor off with pleasing delays.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She (which all this while set solemnly reading in her Book) lent little ear unto his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99084:6"/> words, which he perceiving, pluckt her by the arm, saying: <hi>Wherefore answereth not my fair Love, to her dearest perplexed friend?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What would you have</hi> (quoth she) <hi>can I never be at quiet for you? Is there no corner of content in this world to be found?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes</hi> Winifred, said he, <hi>content dwells here, or no where: content me, and I will content thee, if my content may be thy content: Then read this book, and there rest content,</hi> said Winifred: <hi>and if thou refusest this, then think not to find content on earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> replyed: <hi>What is this all the reward I shall have, for obeying your heart-cutting commands? have I thus long hoped, and find no better hap? You wot well that it is now three long months since these eyes took comfort of thy beauty, and since that time my bleeding heart hath received joy in thy gentleness.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have forgotten you quite,</hi> said she; <hi>What three months is that you speak of? for my part I assure you, that it is as far out of my mind, as you are from the Mount of</hi> Calvary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fair</hi> Winifred (said he) <hi>have you forgotten me and therewithal my love, which I so effectually grounded upon your good liking? You told me that now I should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>receive an answer to my content.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Sir</hi> (quoth she) <hi>you have stayed over-long, and your words are in my hearing as unprofitable as snow in Harvest, my love is fled to Heaven, from whence no earthly man can fet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> it, and therefore build not on vain hope, nor do thou deceive thy self by following any unprofitable suit; if ever I love earthly man it shall be thee, insomuch as thou hast deserved an earthly Ladies love; but my love is setled for ever, both in this world, and in the world to come, and this I most earnestly intreat thee to take for a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal answer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With that Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> turning his head aside, wept most bitterly, and in going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way he glanced his eye back again after his Love, saying to himself: <hi>O unconstant Women, wavering and uncertain, how many sorrows are fond men drawn unto by your wily enticements? who are also swallowed up in the gaping gulph of care, while they listen after the heart-liking sound of your inchanting voices. O</hi> Winifred, <hi>full little did I think that so hard a heart could have been shrouded under so sweet and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a countenance; But seeing that my good will is thus unkindly requited, I will altogether abhor the sight of Women, and I will seek the world throughout, but I will find some blessed plot, where no such kind of corrupt cattle breed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon all in a hot and hasty humour, he made preparation for to go beyond the seas, suiting himself after the nature of a melancholy man, and arriving in <hi>France,</hi> he took his journey towards <hi>Paris,</hi> which City (at that time) was well replenished with many goodly fair women, as well as <hi>Brittain,</hi> though to his thinking nothing so lovely; but nevertheless what they wanted in beauty, they had in bravery: which when Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> saw, he suddenly departed from that place, counting it the most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious place in the whole Countrey: and from thence he went into <hi>Italy,</hi> where he found such stately Dames and lovely Ladies, Whom nature had adorned with all perfection of outward beauty; whose sight put him again in remembrancee of his fair Love, which like fresh fewel newly augmented the flames of his burning desire: <hi>Oh!</hi> (said he) <hi>how unhappy am I to be haunted by these heart-tormenting fiends, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching the eyes of simple men with Angel-like faces, and like inchanting</hi> Circes, <hi>bringing them to a Labyrinth of continual Woes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Winifred, <hi>thy peevishness hath bred my dangers, and done thy self no good at all. Thou sittest weeping by a Crystal stream, where is no need of water, while I wander up and down, seeking to forget thee; thou never remembrest me, having drawn the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99084:6"/> Fountain of mine eyes dry, through thy discourteous disdain. Might <hi>I</hi> never see any of thy Sex, my heart would be more at quiet; but every place where I come puts me in mind of thy perfections, and therewithal renews my pain: but <hi>I</hi> will from hence as soon as possible <hi>I</hi> can, though not so soon as I would, for fear lest these sweet Serpents should sting me to death with delight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon he passed on so far, that at length he came to a City scituated in the sea, and compassed with the wild Ocean. <hi>Here</hi> (quoth Sir <hi>Hugh</hi>) <hi>is a fit place for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy men, where it is supposed that no women do live, insomuch that their delicate bodies cannot endure the salt savour of the mounting waves: If it be so, there will I make my residence, counting it the most blessed place under heaven:</hi> but he was no soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner set on the land, but he beheld whole troops of lovely Ladies, passing up and down in most sumptuous attire, framing their gestures answerable to their beauties and comely personages.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nay, now <hi>I</hi> see</hi> (quoth Sir <hi>Hugh</hi>) <hi>that the whole world is infected with these decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Syrens, and therefore in vain it is for me to seek for that I shall never find;</hi> and there withal sought for some house wherein he might hide himself from them. But by that time he was set at supper, comes a crew of Court-like Dames richly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired, and with wanton eyes and pleasing speech, they boldly sat down by him; and perceiving him to be a stranger, they were not strange to allure him to their delight: wherefore while he sat at meat, they yielded him such mirth as their best skill could afford, and stretched their nimble fingers, playing on their sweet sounding instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they sang this insuing Song, with such clear and quavering voices, as had been sufficient to allure the chast hearted <hi>Xenocrates</hi> unto folly: and still as they did sing Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> answered in the last line: insomuch as it seemed to be a Dialogue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them: And in this manner following the women began their Song.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg type="song">
                     <head>The Curtizens Song of <hi>Venice.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <stage>Ladies</stage> WElcome to <hi>Venice,</hi> gentle courteous Knight,</l>
                        <l>cast off all care, and entertain content,</l>
                        <l>If any here be gracious in thy sight,</l>
                        <l>do but request and she shall soon consent;</l>
                        <l>Loves wings are swift, then be not thou so slow.</l>
                        <l>
                           <stage>Hugh.</stage>
                           <hi>Oh! that fair <hi>Winifred</hi> would once say so.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <stage>Ladies.</stage> Within my lap lay down thy comely head,</l>
                        <l>and let me stroke those golden locks of thine,</l>
                        <l>Look on the tears that for thy sake I shed,</l>
                        <l>and be thou Lord of any thing is mine;</l>
                        <l>One gentle look upon thy Love bestow,</l>
                        <l>
                           <stage>Hugh.</stage>
                           <hi>Oh! that fair <hi>Winifred</hi> would once say so.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <stage>Ladies.</stage> Embrace with joy thy Lady in thine arms,</l>
                        <l>and with all pleasures past to thy delight:</l>
                        <l>If thou dost think the light will work our harms,</l>
                        <l>come, come to bed, and welcome all the night;</l>
                        <l>There shalt thou find what Lovers ought to know,</l>
                        <l>
                           <stage>Hugh.</stage>
                           <hi>Oh! that fair <hi>Winifred</hi> would once say so,</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <stage>Ladies.</stage> Give me those Pearls as pledges of thy Love,</l>
                        <l>and with those Pearls the favour of thy Heart,</l>
                        <l>Do not from me thy sugred breath remove,</l>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:99084:7"/>
                        <l>That double comfort gives to every part:</l>
                        <l>Nay stay Sir Knight, from hence thou shalt not go;</l>
                        <l>
                           <stage>Hugh.</stage>
                           <hi>Oh! that fair <hi>Winifred</hi> would once say so,</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>When Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> had heard this Song, and therewithal noted their wanton ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures, he began to grow suspicious of their proffers, and thinking in himself, that either they thought his destruction, as the <hi>Syrens</hi> did to <hi>Ulysses,</hi> or that they intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make a prey of his purse, as <hi>Lais</hi> did of her Lovers: and therefore supposing some Adder to lye lurking under the fair flowers of their proffered pleasures, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined the next morning after (with spéed) to depart from the City. So when he had with good discretion avoided their company, while he lay tormented with rest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less thoughts on his still tossed bed, began thus to meditate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now well I see mine own vanity, that is as ill pleased with womens favour as their frowns: how often have I with heart sighing sorrow, complained of womens unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, making large invectives against their discourtesies? and yet here where I find women as kind as they are fair, and courteous as they are comely, <hi>I</hi> run into a world of doubts, and am so supicious of their fair proffers, as I was earnest to win</hi> Winifreds <hi>favour. It may be</hi> (quoth he) <hi>that it is the nature of this gentle soyl to breed as kind creatures, as the Country of</hi> Brittain <hi>breeds coy Dames.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Undoubtedly, had my Love first taken life in this kind and courteous Climate, she would have been as kind as they, if I mis-judge not of their gentleness, because <hi>I</hi> have always been turned to scornfulness, methinks they are too fair to he Harlots, and too bold to be honest: but as they have no cause to hate me that never hurt them, so have they little cause to love me, being a far stranger born; to them a man altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, but it may be that this time of the year is only unfortunate for Lovers; as it is certainly known unto all men, that every season of the year breeds a sundry commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, for Roses flourish in</hi> Iune, <hi>and Gilliflowers in</hi> August, <hi>neither of them both doth so in the cold winter. Such as seek for fruit on sapless trees, in the Month of</hi> Ianuary, <hi>lose their labour as well as their longing: then why should <hi>I</hi> covet to gather Fruits of love, when <hi>I</hi> see that love is not yet ripe? Now let me observe the season that yields the sweetest comfort to love-sick persons, and so <hi>I</hi> may reap the joyful Fruits of hearts content; I will therefore return to my former love, hoping now to find her as friendly, as at my departure she was froward: I will once again intreat her, and speak her exceeding fair: for with many drops the hardest stone is pierced; so also with many importunate entreaties, a flinty heart may be moved to some remorse. <hi>I</hi> take no pleasure at all in any place, but only in her presence, with the which she continually graceth a running stream: far be it from her mind to kiss her own shadow in the Crystal Spring, and to be in love with her own similitude, for so she might be spoiled as</hi> Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisus <hi>was; for it is commonly seen that sudden dangers follow fond opinions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So with these, and the like thoughts he drove out the night, till the Suns bright eye began to péep in at his Chamber window, at which time, dressing himself. he went to the water side, where he found a ship ready to transport rich Merchandize to the Western Islands, in the which Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> became a Passenger. But when they were put off to Sea, there arose so sudden a storm, and of a long continuance, that no man looked for life, but expected every moment present death, so that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners quite forsook the Tackle, and the Master the Helm, committing themselves to God, and their Ship to the mercy of the swelling Seas, by whose furious waves they were sometimes tossed up towards heaven, anon thrown down to the deep of hell: in which extremity Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> made this lamentation.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99084:7"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>O unhappy man, how eagerly doth mischance pursue me at my heels; for betwixt my Love on the Land, and danger of life on the Sea, it hath made me the wretchedest man breathing on earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here we may see that miseries have power over men, and not men over miseries: Now must I dye far from my friends, and be drenched in the deep, where my body must feed the fishes that swim in the rich bottom of the Sea: therefore fair</hi> Winifred, <hi>the chief ground of my griefs, here will I Sacrifice my last tears unto thee, and pour forth my complaints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O how happy should <hi>I</hi> count my self, if those fishes which shall live on my bodies food, might be meat for my love! It grieveth me much to think that my poor bleeding heart, wherein thy picture is engraven, should be rent in pieces in such grievous sort: but thrice accursed be that fish that first setteth his nimble teeth thereon, except he swim therewith unto my Love, and so deliver it as a present token from me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Had my troubled Stars allotted me to leave my life in the pleasant valley of</hi> Sichnant, <hi>then no doubt but my Love with her fair hands would have closed up my dying eyes, and perhaps would have rung a peal of sorrowful sighs for my sake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this time was the weather beaten Bark driven by the shore of <hi>Sicilie,</hi> where the men had safety of their lives, although with loss of their Ship, &amp; spoil of their goods, but they had no sooner shaken off their dropping wet garments on the shore, but that they were assaulted by a sort of monstrous men, that had but one eye a piece, and that placed in the midst of their fore-heads: with whom the tempest-beaten Souldiers had a fierce fight, in which many of them were slain, and divers of them fled away, to save themselves: so that in the end Sir, <hi>Hugh</hi> was left alone to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in a double fray: and having at last quite overcome all his adversaries, he went his way, and was so far entred into a dark Wilderness, that he could not devise with himself which way he should take to get out, where he was so cruelly affrighted with the dreadful cry of fierce Lyons and Bears, and wild Bulls and so many thousands more of other dangerous and cruel ravenous Beasts, which with greedy mouths ranged about for their prey, in which distress Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> got him up into tree, and being there brake out into these passions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord</hi> (quoth he) <hi>hast thou preserved me from the great peril and danger of the Sea, and delivered me out of the hand of cruel monstrous men, and now sufferest thou me to be devoured of wild Beasts? Alas, that my foul sins should bring so many sundry sorrows on my head; but for all this may I thank unkind</hi> Winifred, <hi>whose disdain hath wrought my destruction. Wo worth the time that ever I beheld her betwitching beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But hereby we may see that the path is clear that leadeth to danger. But why blame I the blameless Lady? Alas, full little did she know of my desperate courses in travel; but such is the fury that haunts frantick Lovers, that never fear danger until it fall and light upon their own heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But by that time the day began to appear, he perceived a huge Elephant with stiff joynts walking towards him, and presently after came a fiery tongued Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, which suddenly assaulted this peaceful Elephant, in whose subtile encounter, the wrathful Dragon with his long wrinkling tail, did so shackle the hinder feet of the Elephant together, that like a Prisoner fast fettered in irons, he could not stir a foot for his life: at which time the furious Dragon never left till he had thrust his slender head into the Elephants long hooked nose, out of which he never drew it, until by sucking the Elephants blood, he had made him so feeble and so weak, that he could stand no longer upon his feet: at which time, the fainting Elephant with a grievous cry, fell down dead upon the Dragon; so with the fall of his weighty body burst the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99084:8"/> Dragon in pieces, and so killed him; whereby their bloods being mixed together, it stained all the ground where they both lay, changing the green grass into a rich scarlet colour. This strange fight betwixt these two Beasts, caused good Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> to judge that nature had planted betwixt them a deadly hatred, the fire where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of could not be quenched, but by shedding of both their hearts blood. Now when Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> saw that grim death had ended their quarrel, and perceiving no danger near, he came down from the tree, and sought to find out some inhabited town: but being intangled in the VVoods, like the <hi>Centaur</hi> in his Labyrinth, he could by no means get out, but wandred in unknown passages, leading him to many perils.</p>
               <p>At last another Elephant met him, who according to his kind nature never left him till he had conducted him out of all danger, and brought him out of the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness into the way again, whereby Sir <hi>Hguh</hi> at the length came in sight of a Port-Town, where in four days after he imbarqued himself in a Ship bound for <hi>Brittain,</hi> and at last obtained the sight of his Native Countrey, where he arrived in safety, though in a very poor sort, coming on shore at a place called <hi>Harwich,</hi> where for want of money he greatly lamented, and made much moan. But meeting with a merry Iourney-man Shoomaker dwelling in that Town, and after some conference had together, they both agreed to travel in the Countrey, where we will leave them, and speak of <hi>Winifred,</hi> and of her great troubles and calamities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. How fair <hi>Winifred</hi> was imprisoned and condemned to dye for her Religion; and how Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> became a Shoomaker, and afterwards came to suffer death with his Love; shewing also how the Shoomakers tools came to be called St. <hi>Hugh</hi>'s Bones; and the trade of Shoomaking the <hi>Gentle-Craft.</hi>
               </head>
               <figure/>
               <p>ANon atfer the Doctrine of Christ was made known in <hi>Brittain,</hi> &amp; that the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of Heathen Idols was forbidden, yet many troubles did the Christians en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure by the out-ragious blood-thirstiness of divers wolfish Tyrants, that by the way of invasion set footing in this Land, as it fell out in the days of <hi>Dioclesian,</hi> that with bloody minds persecuted such as would not yield to the Pagan Law, among which the Virgin <hi>Winifred</hi> was one, who for that she continued constant in the faith, was long imprisoned. During which time, Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> wrought in a Shoomakers-shop having learned that trade through the courteous directions of a kind Iourney-man, where be remain'd the space of one whole year, in which time he had gotten himself good ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99084:8"/> and every thing comely and decent. Notwithstanding, though he were now contented to forget his birth, yet could not be forget the beauty of his Love: who although he had utterly forsaken her, yet could he not alter his affections from her, because indeed affections alter not, like a pale-faced Coward. <hi>The wildest Bull</hi> (quoth he) <hi>is tamed, being tyed to a Fig-tree, and the coyest Dame (in time) may yield, like Wax. Though Roses have prickles, yet they are gathered; and though Women seem froward, yet they will shew themselves kind and friendly. Neither is there any Wax so hard, but by often tempering, is made apt to receive an impression. Admit she hath heretofore been cruel, yet now may she be courteous. A true-hearted Lover forgets all trespasses, and a smile cureth the wound of a frown.</hi> Thus after the manner of fond Lovers, he flattered himself in his own folly, and in the praise of his fair La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, he sang this pleasant Ditty here following.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg type="song">
                     <lg>
                        <l>THe Pride of <hi>Brittain</hi> is my hearts delight,</l>
                        <l>My Lady lives, my true love to requite:</l>
                        <l>And in her life I live, that else were dead,</l>
                        <l>Like withered leaves in time of Winter shed.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>She is the joy and comfort of my mind,</l>
                        <l>She is the Sun that clearest sight doth blind,</l>
                        <l>The fairest Flower that in the world doth grow,</l>
                        <l>Whose whiteness doth surpass the driven Snow.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Her gentle words more sweet than Honey are,</l>
                        <l>Her eyes for clearness dim the brightest Star:</l>
                        <l>Oh! were her heart so kind as she is fair,</l>
                        <l>No Lady might with my true love compare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A thousand griefs for her I have sustained,</l>
                        <l>While her proud thoughts my humble suit disdained,</l>
                        <l>And tho she would my heart with torments kill,</l>
                        <l>Yet would I honour, serve, and love her still.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Blest be the place where she doth like to live,</l>
                        <l>Blest be the light that doth her comfort give;</l>
                        <l>And blessed be all creatures far and near,</l>
                        <l>That yield Relief unto my Lady dear.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Never may sorrow enter where she is,</l>
                        <l>Never may she contented comfort miss,</l>
                        <l>Never may she my proffered Love forsake:</l>
                        <l>But my good will in thankful sort to take.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Thus feeding his fancy with the sweet remembrance of her beauty, being never satisfied with thinking and speaking to her praise, at length he resolved himself to go into <hi>Flint-shire,</hi> where he might solicite his suit anew again; but coming near to the place of her residence, and hearing report of her troubles, he so highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended her faith &amp; constancy that at length he was clapt up in Prison by her; and in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99084:9"/> the end he was condemned to receive equal torment for a tryal of his own truth.</p>
               <p>But during the time that they lay both in Prison, the Iourney-men Shoomakers never left him, but yielded him great relief continually, so that he wanted nothing that was necessary for him: In requital of which kindness, he called them <hi>Genthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Gentle Craft:</hi> and a few days before his death, he made this Song in their due commendations.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg type="song">
                     <lg>
                        <l>OF Craft and Crafts-men more or less, the Gentle-Craft I must commend,</l>
                        <l>Whose deeds declare their faithfulness, and hearty Love unto their Friend.</l>
                        <l>The Gentle-Craft in midst of strife,</l>
                        <l>Yields comfort to a careful Life.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Prince by birth <hi>I</hi> am indeed, the which for Love forsook this Land,</l>
                        <l>And when I was in extream need, I took the Gentle-Craft in hand:</l>
                        <l>And by the Gentle-Craft alone,</l>
                        <l>Long time I liv'd being still unknown.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Spending my days in sweet content, with many a pleasant sugred Song,</l>
                        <l>Sitting with pleasures complement, whilst we recorded lovers wrong:</l>
                        <l>And while the Gentle-Craft we us'd,</l>
                        <l>True love by us was not abus'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Our Shooes we sowed with merry notes, and by our mirth expel'd all moan,</l>
                        <l>Like Nightingals, from whose sweet throats, most pleasant Tunes are nightly blown,</l>
                        <l>The Gentle-Craft is fittest then,</l>
                        <l>For poor distressed Gentlemen.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Their minds do mount in courtesie, and they disdain a niggards Feast,</l>
                        <l>Their Bodies are for Chivalry, all Cowardise they do detest:</l>
                        <l>For Sword and Shield, for Bow and Shaft,</l>
                        <l>No man can stain the Gentle-Craft.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yea, sundry Princes sore distrest, shall seek for succour by this Trade,</l>
                        <l>Whereby their griefs shall be redrest, of Foes they shall not be afraid:</l>
                        <l>And many men of Fame likewise,</l>
                        <l>Shall from this Gentle-Craft arise.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If we want Money over-night, ere next day noon God will it send,</l>
                        <l>Thus we may keep our selves upright, and be no Churls unto our Friend:</l>
                        <l>Thus do we live where pleasure springs,</l>
                        <l>In our conceit like petty Kings.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Our hearts with care, we may not kill, mans life surpasseth worldly Wealth,</l>
                        <l>Content surpasseth riches still, and fie on Knaves that live by stealth:</l>
                        <l>This Trade therefore both great and small,</l>
                        <l>The Gentle-Craft shall ever call.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>When the Iourney-men Shoomakers had heard this Song, and the fair title that Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> had given their Trade: they ingraved the same so deeply in their minds,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99084:9"/> that to this day it could never be razed out, like a remembrance in a Marble-stone which continueth time out of mind.</p>
               <p>But not long after came the doleful day, wherein these two Lovers must lose their lives, who like two meek Lamb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were led to the slaughter: the bloody performance thereof was to be done hard by that fair Fountain, where the Love despi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ng Lady made her most abode: and because she was a Kings daughter, the bloody Tyrant gave her the Priviledge to chuse her own death: to the which she passed with as good a countenance, as if she had been a fair young Bride prepared for Marriage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>(Viz)</hi> When they were come to the place of execution, and mounted on the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, they seemed for beauty like two bright stars, <hi>Castor</hi> and <hi>Pollux;</hi> there they embraced each other with such chast desire, as all those that beheld them, admi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed to see how stedfast and firm both these Lovers were, ready in hearts and minds to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it self.</p>
               <p>At what time the Lady turned her self to Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> and spake to this effect: <hi>Now <hi>I</hi> find thee a perfect Lover indeed, that having setled thy affections above the Skies, art ready to yield thy life for thy love, who in requital thereof, will give thee thy life for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The love of earthly creatures is mixed with many miseries, and interlaced with sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry sorrows; and here grief shall abate the pleasures of love, but be well assured that you shall follow the same.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou didst wooe me for love, and now I have won thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o love, where setling both our selves upon God his love, we will love one another: and in token of that heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly love, receive of me, I pray thee, a chast and loving kiss from my dying lips.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fair Winifred</hi> (<abbr>qd</abbr> he) <hi>it is true indeed, I never loved truly, till thou taughtest me to love, for then my love was full of discontent; but now altogether pleasing, and more sweet to the thought thereof, than any one can express.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The thing that I before ever called love, was but a shadow of love; a sweetness tempered with gall, a dying life, and a living death; where the heart was continually tossed upon the Seas of tempestuous sorrows, and wherein the mind had no calm quietness: And therefore blessed be the time that I ever learned this love,</hi> With that he was interrupted by the Tyrant, who said, <hi>You are not come hither to talk, but to dye: I have sworn you shall both dye at this instant. Thou Tyrant</hi> (said Sir <hi>Hugh</hi>) <hi>the very like sentence is pronounced against thy self: for Nature hath doomed that thou shalt dye likewise, and albeit the execution thereof be something deferred, yet at length it will come, and that shortly, for never did Tyrant carry gray hairs to the Grave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The young Lady desired first to dye, saying to Sir <hi>Hugh, Come dear friend, and learn magnanimity of a Maid: now shalt thou see a silly woman scorn death at his teeth, and make as small account of his cruelty, as the Tyrant doth of our lives;</hi> and therewithal stript up her silken sleeves and committed her Alabaster Arms into the Executioners foul hands, having made choise to dye bleeding: at what time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pricked in every vein, the scarlet blood sprang out in plentiful sort, much like a precious Fountain lately filled with Claret-wine.</p>
               <p>And while she thus bled, she said; <hi>Here do I sacrifice my blood to him that bought me, who by his blood wash away all my sins; O my sweet Saviour, thus were thy sides pierced for any trangressions, and in this sort sprang thy precious blood from thee, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> for the love thou barest to mankind: I feel my Heart to faint, but my Soul receiveth strength, I come sweet Christ, I come.</hi> And therewithal her body fainting and the blood failing, like a Conduit drawn dry, the young Princess fell down
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99084:10"/> dead, at what time a pale colour over spread her fair face in such comely sort as if a heap of Roses had been shadowed with a sheet of pure Lawn.</p>
               <p>But it is to be remembred, that all the while the young Princess bled, her blood was received into certain basons, which being in that sort saved together, the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant caused it to be tempered with poyson, and prepared it to be the last drink that Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> should have: saying, <hi>that by her love whom he so dearly loved, he should receive his death.</hi> And thereupon incontinently, without any farther delay of time, he caused a cup of the most deadly poysoned blood to be delivered into his hands, who with a lovely and chearful countenance received the same, and then uttered his mind in this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O thou cruel Tyrant</hi> (quoth he) <hi>what a poor spight is this to inflict upon a dying Man, that is as careless how he dies, as when he dies: Easie it is for thee to glut me with blood, although with blood thou art not satisfied. Sweet blood</hi> (quoth he) <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and pure, how fair a colour dost thou cast before mine eyes? sweet, I say, wast thou, before such time as this ill-savouring Poyson did infect thee: And yet as thou art I nothing despise thee: O my dear</hi> Winifred, <hi>full litle did I think that ever I should come to drink of thy heart blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My greedy eye, that glutton-like did feed upon thy beauty, and yet like the Sea, was never satisfied, is now with gore-blood fully gorged. Now may I quench my thirsty desire with love, that like hot burning coals set my heart in such an extream heat, that it could not be quenched before this time; for if fair</hi> Winifred <hi>could spare any love from heaven, assuredly she left it in her blood, her sweet heart blood I mean, that nourished her chast life: see here is a Candle to cool my vain affections. Far be it that any true lovers should ever taste the like.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But this punishment hath the just heavens poured upon me, for the preferring the love of an earthly creature, before the love of an heavenly Creator; Pardon, O Lord, the foul sins of superstitious Lovers, that while they make Idols of their Ladies, they forget the honour of thy divine Majesty. Yet doth it do my heart good to think that I must bury sweet</hi> Winifreds <hi>blood in my body, whose love was lodged long ago in my heart:</hi> and therewithal drinking the first draught; he said: <hi>O Lord, me seemeth this portion hath a comfortable taste, far doth it surpass the Nectar wherewith the Gods were nourished.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well</hi> (said the Tyrant) <hi>seeing it pleaseth thee so well, thou shalt have more;</hi> And therewith another cup of the same blood was given him to drink.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yea, come</hi> (quoth he) <hi>my thirst is not yet quenched, for the first draught gave me but a taste of sweetness, and like a longing woman, I desire the rest:</hi> and with that he drank the second draught. The third being given him; he took the Cup into his hand, and looking about, he said; <hi>Lo here I drink to all the kind Yeomen of the Gentle-Craft.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I drink to you all</hi> (quoth he) <hi>but I cannot spare you one drop to pledge me. Had I any good thing to give you, you should soon receive it; but my life the Tyrant doth take, and my flesh is bequeathed to the Fowls. So that nothing is left but only my bones to pleasure you withal, and those if they will do you any good, take them: and so I humbly take my leave, bidding you all farewel.</hi> There with the last draught he finished his life; whose dead Carcass was hanged up, where the Fowls devoured his flesh; and the young Princess was contemptuously buried by the Well, where she had so long lived. Then had he the title of St. <hi>Hugh</hi> given him, and she of St. <hi>Winifred,</hi> by which terms they are both so called to this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99084:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. How the Shoomakers stole away St. <hi>Hugh</hi>'s bones, and made them working tools there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and the virtue that they found in the same: whereby it came, that when any man saw a Shoomaker travelling with a Pack at his back, they would presently say, <hi>There goes St, <hi>Hugh</hi>'s bones.</hi>
               </head>
               <figure/>
               <p>UPon a time it chanced that a company of Iourney-men Shoomakers passed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long by the place where St, <hi>Hugh</hi>'s dead body was hanged, and finding the flesh pickt clean off from the bones, they entred thus into communication among themselves:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Never was St.</hi> Hugh <hi>so bare</hi> (quoth one) <hi>to carry never a whit of skin upon his bones; nor thou never so bare</hi> (saith another) <hi>to bear never a Penny in thy purse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now hearing you talk of St. <hi>Hugh</hi> it brings me to remembrance of his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacy that he gave us at his Death: <hi>What was that?</hi> said the rest: <hi>Mary</hi> (quoth he) <hi>I will tell you; when the gentle Prince saw that the cruelty of the time would not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for him to be liberal to his friends, but that his life was taken away by one, and his flesh given to others, he most kindly bequeathed his bones unto us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tush</hi> (<abbr>qd</abbr> another) <hi>that was but to shew his mind towards the Shoomakers, because he had received of them so many favors; For alas, what can the dead mans bones plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure the living? No</hi> (<abbr>qd</abbr> another) <hi>I can tell you, there may be as great vertue found in his bones as in the brain of a Weasil, or the tongue of a Frog: Much like</hi> (answered the rest) <hi>but I pray thee shew us what virtue is in those things you speak of.</hi> Quoth he, <hi>I will tell you: The brains of a Weasil hath this power,</hi> experientia docet, <hi>that if the powder thereof be mingled with Runnet, wherewith women make their Cheese, no Mouse dares touch it: In like manner, the tongue of a Water-Frog hath such great force in it, that if it be laid upon the Breast of any one sleeping, it will cause them to tell whatsoever you shall demand; for by that means</hi> Dick Piper <hi>knew he was a Cuck old. Again, I know that those that are Travellers, are not ignorant that whosoever puts but six leaves of Mugwort in his Shooes, shall never be weary, though he travel thirty or forty miles on foot a forenoon. That indeed may be true,</hi> quoth one, <hi>for by the very same Herb my last Dame kept her Ale from sowring: And it it said, That where Housleek is planted, the place shall never be hurt with thunder: Pimpernel is good against Whitchcraft: and because my Sister</hi> Ioan <hi>carried always some about her, Mother</hi> Bumby <hi>could not abide her: therefore what vertue a dead mans bones may have, we know not till we have tryed them.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99084:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why then,</hi> said the third man, <hi>let us soon at night steal St.</hi> Hugh's <hi>bones away, and albeit the Tyrant will be displeased, yet it is no theft: for you say they were given us, and therefore we may the bolder take them, and because we will turn them to profit and avoid suspicion, we will make divers of our tools with them, and then if any virtue doth follow them, the better we shall find it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this motion every one gave his consent, so that the same night St. <hi>Hugh's</hi> bones were taken down, and the same being brought before a sort of Shoomakers there they gave their opinion, That it was necessary to fulfil the will of the dead, and to take those bones as in good part, as if they were worth ten thousand pounds; whereupon one stept out and thus did say:
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>MY Friends I pray you list to me,</l>
                        <l>And mark what St. <hi>Hugh</hi>'s bones shall be</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>FIrst a Drawer and a Dresser,</l>
                        <l>Two Wedges, a more and a lesser:</l>
                        <l>A pretty block three inches high,</l>
                        <l>In Fashion squared like a Dye;</l>
                        <l>Which shall be called by proper name,</l>
                        <l>A Heel-block, the very same:</l>
                        <l>A hard leather, and a thumb-leather likewise,</l>
                        <l>To pull out shoo-thred we must devise;</l>
                        <l>The Needle and the Thimble shall not be left alone,</l>
                        <l>The Princers, and the Pricking Aul, and rubbing Stone;</l>
                        <l>The Aul, steel, and Iacks, the Sowing Hairs beside,</l>
                        <l>The Stirrop, holding fast, while we sow the Cow-hide:</l>
                        <l>The Whet-stone, the Stopping-stick, and the paring knife,</l>
                        <l>All this doth belong to a Journey-mans life:</l>
                        <l>Our Apron is the Shrine to wrap these bones in;</l>
                        <l>Thus shroud we St. <hi>Hugh</hi>'s bones in a gentle Lambs skin.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now all you good Yeomen of the Gentle-Craft,</hi> (<hi>tell me now</hi> quoth he) <hi>how like you this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As well</hi> (replied they) <hi>as St.</hi> George <hi>doth of his horse; for as long as we can see him fight with the Dragon, we will never part from this Posie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And it shall be concluded, that what Journey-man soever he be hereafter, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not handle his Sword nor Buckler, his Long-sword, or a Quarter staff, sound the Trumpet, or play upon the Flute, and bear his part in a three mans Song, and readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reckon up his tools in Rhime, except he have born Colours in the field, being a Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, a Sergeant, or Corpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l shall forfeit and pay a pottle of Wine, or be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a Colt,</hi> to which they answered all, <hi>Viva voce, Content, content:</hi> and then after many merry songs they departed. And never after did they travel without these Tools on their backs: which ever since were called St. <hi>Hugh</hi>'s bones.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:99084:11"/>
               <head>CAHP. V. How <hi>Crispianus</hi> &amp; his Brother <hi>Crispin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> the two Sons of the King of <hi>Logria</hi> (through the cruelty of the Tyrant <hi>Maximinus</hi>) were fain in disguised manner to seek for their lives safety, and how they were entertained by a Shoomaker in <hi>Feversham.</hi>
               </head>
               <figure/>
               <p>WHen the Roman <hi>Maximinus</hi> sought in cruel sort to bereave this Land of all her Noble Youth, or Youth of Noble blood: the vertuous Queen of <hi>Logria</hi> (which now is called <hi>Kent</hi>) dwelled in the City <hi>Durovenum alias Canterbury,</hi> or the Court of Kentish men, having at that time two young Sons, sought all the means she could possible to keep them out of the Tyrants claws: and in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner she spake unto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My dear and beloved Sons; the joy and comfort of my age, you see the dangers of these times, and the storms of a Tyrants Reign, who having now gathered together the most part of the young Nobility, to make them slaves in a forreign Land, that are free-born in their own Country, seeketh for you also, thereby to make a clear riddance of all our born Princes, to the end he might plant strangers in their stead: Therefore (my sweet sons) take the counsel of your Mother, and seek in time to prevent ensuing danger, which will come upon us as suddenly as a storm at Sea, and as cruelly as a Tyger in the Wilderness, therefore suiting your selves in honest habits, seek some poor service to shield you from mischance, seeing necessity hath priviledged those places from Tyranny. And so (my Sons) the gracious Heavens may one day raise you to deserved dignity and honour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The young Lads, seeing that their Mother was so earnest to have them gone, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled her Commandment, and casting off their attire, put homely garments on, and with many bitter tears took leave of the Queen their Mother, desiring her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they went to bestow her blessing upon them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O my Sons</hi> (quoth she) <hi>stand you now upon your ceremonies? Had I leisure to give you one kiss, it were something, the Lord bless you, get you go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e; away, away, make hast I say, let not swift time overslip you, for the Tyrant is hard by:</hi> with that she pushed them out of a back door, and then sets her self down to weep.</p>
               <p>The two young Princes, which like pretty Lambs went straying they knew not whither, at length by good fortune came to <hi>Feversham,</hi> where before the day peep they heard certain Shoomakers singing, being as pleasant at their Notes, as they sat at their business: and this was their Song.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:99084:12"/>
               <q>
                  <lg type="song">
                     <lg>
                        <l>WOuld God that it were Holiday,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey derry down, down derry;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>That with my love I might go play,</l>
                        <l>with woe my heart is weary:</l>
                        <l>My whole delight is in her sight,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>would God I had her company, her company;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hey derry down, down a down.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My love is fine, my love is fair,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey derry down, down derry.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>No Maid may well with her compare,</l>
                        <l>in <hi>Kent</hi> or <hi>Canterbury;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>From me my Love shall never move,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>would God I had company, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To see her laugh, to see her smile,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey derry down, down derry,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Doth all my sorrows clean beguile,</l>
                        <l>and makes my heart full merry:</l>
                        <l>No grief doth grow where she doth go,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>would God I had her company, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>When I do meet her on the green,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey derry down, down derry,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Methinks she looks like beauties Queen,</l>
                        <l>which makes my heart full merry;</l>
                        <l>Then I her greet with kisses sweet;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>would God I had her company, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My love comes not of churlish kind,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey derry down, down derry;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But bears a loving courteous mind,</l>
                        <l>which makes my heart full merry;</l>
                        <l>She is not coy, she is my joy,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>would God I had her company, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Till Sunday come, farewel my Dear,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey derry down, down derry;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>When we do meet we'l have good chear,</l>
                        <l>and then I will be merry:</l>
                        <l>If thou love me, I will love thee;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>and still delight in thy company, thy company:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hey derry down, down a down.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>The young Princes perceiving such mirth to remain in so homely a Cottage, judged by their pleasant Notes, that their hearts were not cloyed with over much cares; and therefore wished it might be their good hap to be harbored in a place of such great content.</p>
               <p>But standing a long time in doubt what to do, like two distressed strangers, comba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting betwixt hope and fear, at length taking courage, <hi>Crispianus</hi> knocked at the door: What Knave knocks there (quoth one of the Iourney-men) and by and by he takes his Quarter-staff, and opens the door, being as ready to strike as to speak: saying, <hi>What lack you?</hi> To whom <hi>Crispianus</hi> made this answer: <hi>Good Sir pardon our bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and measure not our truth by our rudeness, we are two poor boys that want service, stript from our friends by the fury of these wars, and therefore are we enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced succourless to crave service in any place: What, have you no friends or acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in these parts to go to</hi> (said the Shoomaker) <hi>by whose means you might get pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment? Alas Sir</hi> (said <hi>Crispianus</hi>) <hi>necessity is despised of every one, and misery is trodden down of many, but seldom or never reliev'd: Yet notwithstanding, if our hope did not yield us some comfort of good hap, we should grow desperate through distress. That were great pity</hi> (said the Shoomaker) <hi>be content, for as our Dame tells our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, a patient man is better than a strong man: Stay a while, and <hi>I</hi> will call our Dame to the door, and then you shall hear what she will say.</hi> With that he went in and forth came his Dame, who beholding the said youths, said: <hi>Now alas poor Boys, how comes it pass that you are out of service? What, would you be Shoomakers, and learn the Gentle Craft? Yes forsooth,</hi> said they, <hi>with all our hearts. Now by my troth,</hi>
                  <abbr>qd</abbr> she <hi>you do look with honest true faces, I will intreat my Husband for you, for we would g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>adly have good Boys; and if you will be just and true, and serve God, no doubt but you may do well enough; Come in my Lads; come in. Crispianus</hi> and his Brother, with great reverence gave her thanks: and by that time they had stayed a little while, down came the good man, and his Wife hard by his heels, saying, <hi>See Husband, these be the youths I told you of, no doubt but in time they will be good men.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:99084:12"/>
               <p>Her Husband looking wishtly upon them, and conceiving a good opinion of their favors, at length agreed that they should dwell with him, so that they would be bound for seven years. The youths being contented, the bargain was soon ended, and so set to their business, whereat they were no sooner setled, but that great search was made for them in all places; and albeit the Officers came to the house where they dwelt, by reason of their disguise they knew them not: having also taken upon them bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed names of <hi>Crispianus</hi> and <hi>Crispine.</hi> Within a few days after the Queen their Mother was by the Tyrant taken, and for that she would not confess where her Sons were, she was laid in Prison in <hi>Colchester</hi> Castle, whereunto she went with as chearful a countenance as <hi>Cateratus</hi> did, when he was led captive to <hi>Rome;</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the place where her Sons sat at work, with a quick eye she had soon espyed them: &amp; look how a dying Coal revives in the wind, even so at this sight she became suddenly red: but making signs that they should hold their tongues, she was led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long: whom seven years after her Sons did never see. But as men stand amazed at the sight of Apparitions in the Air, as ignorant of what success shall follow; even so were these two Princes agast to see their own Mother thus led away, not knowing what danger should ensue thereof.</p>
               <p>Notwithstanding they thought good to keep their service, as their lives surest re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge: at what time they both bent their whole minds to please their Master and Dame, refusing nothing that was put them to do: were it to wash-dishes, scoure kettles, or any other thing, whereby they thought their Dames favour might be gotten, which made her the readier to give them a good report to their Master, and to do them any other service, which otherwise they should have missed, following there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the admonition of an old journey man, who would always say to the Apprentices:
<q>
                     <l>Howsoever things do frame,</l>
                     <l>Please well thy Master, but chiefly thy Dame,</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now by that time these two young Princes had truly served their Master the space of four or five years, he was grown somewhat wealthy, and they very cunnning in their Trade, whereby the house had the name to bréed the best work-men in the Country, which report in the end, preferred their Master to be the Emperors Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker: and by this means his servants went to <hi>Maximinus</hi> Court every day: but <hi>Cris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pianus</hi> and <hi>Crispine,</hi> fearing they should have been known, kept themselves from thence as much as they could: Notwithstanding, at the last perswading themselves that time had worn them out of knowledge, they were willing in the end to go thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as well to hear tidings of the Quéen their Mother; as also to seek their own preferment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. How the Emperours fair Daughter <hi>Vrsula,</hi> fell in love with young <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>pine,</hi> coming with Shooes to the Court, and how in the end they were secretly Married by a blind Fryer.</head>
               <p>NOw among all the Shoomakers men that came to the Court with Shooes, young <hi>Crispine</hi> was had in greatest esteem with the fair Princess, whose Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being lately dead, she was the only joy of her Father, who always sought means to match her with some worthy <hi>Roman,</hi> whose renown might ring through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole World.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:99084:13"/>
               <figure/>
               <p>But fair <hi>Ursula</hi> whose bright eyes had entangled her heart with desire of the Shoomakers favor, despised all proffers of Love in regard of him. And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing she would oft check her own opinion, in placing her love upon a person of such low degree: thus reasoning with her self.</p>
               <p>Most aptly is the God of Love by cunning Painters drawn blind, that so unequal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly shoots forth his fiery shafts: for had he eyes to see, it were impossible to deal in such sort as in matching <hi>Venus</hi> with foul <hi>Vulcan,</hi> yoking the Emperial hearts of Kings to the love of Beggars, as he did to <hi>Cosetua</hi> &amp; as now in my self: I find how mad a thing it would seem to the eyes of the world, than an Emperours daughters should delight in the favor of a simple Shoomaker.</p>
               <p>O <hi>Ursula,</hi> take heed what thou dost, stain not thy royalty with such indignity. O that <hi>Crispines</hi> birth were agreeable to his person! for in mine eye, there is no Prince in the World comparable to him: if then while he is cloathed with these rags of servitude, he appears so excellent, what would he be, were he in Princely attire? O <hi>Crispine!</hi> either thou art not as thou seemest, or else Nature, in disgrace of Kings hath made thee a Shoomaker.</p>
               <p>In these humours would the Princess be often, especially at <hi>Crispines</hi> approach, or at his departure. For as soon as ever he came within her sight with shooes, a sudden blush, like a flash of lightning, would strike in her face, &amp; at his departure an earthly pale colour, like the beams of the bright Sun, obscured by coal black clouds. But after many weary conflicts with fancy, she fully resolved at his next coming, to enter into communication with him, but imagining his stay from the Court over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, on the sudden she sent presently for him, finding great fault with the last shooes he brought her; at which time <hi>Crispine</hi> most humbly on his knee, greatly craved par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for all such faults as she then found, promising amendment in the next Shooes she should have.</p>
               <p>Nay (quoth she) I'l shew thee, they are too low something in the instep: also the heel is had; and besides they are too strait in the toes: You shall have a pair made (said he) shall fit you better, for none shall set a stitch in them but mine own self: do, said the Princess, but let me have them so soon as thou canst, and therewith <hi>Cris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine</hi> departed.</p>
               <p>The Princess then all solitary, got her self into her Chamber, entred there into consideration, and found within her self great trouble and sorrow, while the tongue the hearts advocate was not suffered to speak. At last she heard <hi>Crispines</hi> voice, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99084:13"/> of the Ladies in the great Chamber, for the Princess: who answered that having taking little rest the night before, she was now laid down to sleep, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they willed him to come again some other time: <hi>Asleep,</hi> replyed the Princess, <hi>I am not asleep, bid him stay: what hasty Huswife was that which sent him hence: call him again quickly I would advise you.</hi> And therefore changing melancholy into Mirth, she arose up from out of her bed, &amp; as a bright Star shooting in the Element she quickly got her forth to meet the Shoomaker, whose fair sight was to her as great a comfort, as a Sunshine before a shoure of Rain. <hi>How now</hi> (quoth she) <hi>hast thou brought me a pair of Shooes? I have gracious Madam</hi> (quoth he) <hi>Then</hi> (quoth the Princess) <hi>come thy self and draw them on.</hi> Therewith she sitting down, lifted up her well proportioned Leg upon his gentle Knee: where by that time her Shooes were drawn on, she had prepared a good reward for her Shoomaker: and giving him a handful of Gold, she said: <hi>Thou hast so well pleased me in making of these Shooes, that I cannot but reward thee in some good sort: Therefore Shoomaker take this, and from henceforth let no man make my Shooes but thy self. But tell me</hi> Crispine, <hi>art thou not in love, that thou dost smug up thy self so finely, thou wast not wont to go so near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? I pray thee tell me what pretty Wench it is that is Mistriss of thy Heart? Truly fair Madam</hi> (quoth he) <hi>if I should not love, I might be accounted barbarous, for by Natures course, there is a mutual love in all things, the Dove and the Peacock love in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely, so doth the Turtle and the Popinjay; the like affection the fish Musculus bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the huge Whale, insomuch that he leadeth him from all danger of stony Rocks. And as amongst Birds and fishes, so amongst Plants and Trees, the like concord is to be found: for if the Male of Palm Trees be planted from the Female, neither of both prosper: and being set one near another, they flourish accordingly: imbracing with joy the branches of one another. And for mine own part, I am in love too: For first of all I love my Maker, and next my good Master and Dame: but as concerning the love of pretty Wenches, verily Madam I am clear, and the rather do I abstain from fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my fancy on woman, seeing so many sorrows do follow the Married sort; for a dram of delight hath a pound of pain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That is</hi> (answered the Princess) <hi>where contention setteth the house on fire, but where true love remains there is no discontent; and what can a man more desire for this worlds comfort, but a vertuous Wife, which is reported to be a treasure inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable. Therefore</hi> Crispine, <hi>say thy mind, if I prefer thee to a Wife, every way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving of thy love, wouldst thou take it well?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Truly Madam</hi> (said <hi>Crispine</hi>) <hi>if I should not accept of your good will, I should shew my self more unmannerly than well nurtured. But seeing it pleaseth you to grace me with your Princely countenance, and to give me liberty to speak my mind, this is my opinion: If I were to chuse a Wife, then would I have one, Fair, Rich, and Wise: First to delight mine eye; Secondly, to supply my want: And Thirdly, to govern my House.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then</hi> (said the Princess) <hi>her beauty will I refer unto the Judgment of thine own eyes, and her wisdom unto the tryal of time: but as concerning her Portion, I dare make some report, because it well deserveth to be praised: For at her Marriage thou shalt have a bag of rare Vertues with her. Truly Madam</hi> (quoth <hi>Crispin</hi>) <hi>such Coyne go not currant among Tanners: and I know if I should go with it to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, it would buy me no Sole-Leather. Notwithstanding, when I do see her, I will tell you more of my mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Princess taking him aside privately, walking with him in a fair Gallery, said, <hi>In looking upon me thou mayst judge of her, for she is as like me as may be:</hi> when
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99084:14"/>
                  <hi>Crispine</hi> heard her say so, he right prudently answered, <hi>I had rather Madam she were your own self, than like your self: and although my words favour of presumption, yet with your favour I dare boldly pronounce it, that I hold my self worthy of a Queen, if I could get her good will: and were it no danger to match with your Excellency, so it should please you, it should not dislike me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then said the Princess, <hi>Now Shoomaker, I see thou hast some courage in thee; and doubt thou not, but if I were of that mind, I would be as ready to guide thee from the dangerous Rocks of my Fathers wrath, as the fish called Musculus is for the Whale; But could thou be contented to dye for a Ladies love? No, Madam</hi> (quoth he) <hi>if I could keep her love and live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then live fair friend</hi> (answered she) <hi>enjoy my love, for I will rather dye than live without thee. Crispine</hi> hearing this was stricken into an extasie of joy, in such sort as he wist not whether he was asleep or dreamed: But by that time he had summoned his wits together, with the plighting his Faith, he opened his Estate and High Birth unto her, shewing all the extremities that he and his Brother had been put unto, since the death of their Royal Father, and of the imprisonment of the Queen their Mother.</p>
               <p>The which when fair <hi>Ursula</hi> with great wonder heard, giving an earnest of her love, with a sweet Kiss she said: <hi>My dear love and most gentle Prince, ever did I think that more than a common man was shrouded in these poor Habiliments, which made me the bolder to impart my mind unto thee; and now dread no more my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wrath, for the fire thereof was long ago quenched.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No no</hi> (quoth <hi>Crispine</hi>) <hi>an Eagles thirst is never expelled but by blood. And albeit your Father have now (perhaps) qualified the heat of his fury by the length of time, yet if he should understand of this my love to thee, it would cause him to take out of the ashes hot burning coals of displeasure again, and then might my life pay a dear price for thy love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore</hi> (<hi>my dear</hi> Vrsula) <hi>I desire thee, even by the power of that love thou bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est to me, to keep secret what I have shewed to thee, nothing doubting but that in time I may find release of these miseries; in the mean space we will be secretly Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, by which holy Knot; we as well in body as in heart may be unseparably tyed together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this <hi>Ursula</hi> consented most gladly; and thereupon told him that she would meet him in her Fathers Park, at any hour he would appoint. Which she might do the more easily, in respect she had a Key to one of the Garden doors, which gave yresent passage into the Park. The day and hour being concluded upon, they parted for this time both of them indued with such content, as in all their lives they never found the like.</p>
               <p>And at this time there was in <hi>Canterbury</hi> a bind Fryer, that in many years had never seen the Sun, to this man did <hi>Crispine</hi> go, thinking him the fittest Chaplain to chop up such a Marriage, who meeting with him at <hi>Christ-Church</hi> one evening after the Anthem, broke with him after this manner:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God speed you good father: there is a certain friend of mine that would be secretly Married in the Morning betimes, for which purpose he thinks you the fittest man to perform it in all the Cloyster; and therefore if you will be diligent to do it, and secret to conceal it, you shall have four Angels for your pains.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fryer being fired with the desire of his gold, rubbing his Clbow, and scratch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Crown swore by the blessed book that hung by his knee that he would be both willing, and constant to keep it secret. <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> young man, you may trust me, I have done
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99084:14"/> many of these fears in my days; I know that youth are youth, but they would not have all the world wonder at their doings. And where shall it be,</hi> said the Fryer? Quoth <hi>Crispine, at St.</hi> Gregories <hi>Chappel: and because you shall not make your boy acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therewith, I my self will call you in the morning. Good Father be not forgetful to observe the time, at two of the Clock is the hour, and therefore look you be ready when I call you: I warrant you</hi> (replyed the Fyer); <hi>and because I will not over-sleep my self, I will for this night lie in my clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>hs: so that as soon as ever you call, I will streight be ready: Then Father I will trust to you,</hi> (quoth <hi>Crispine</hi>) and so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</p>
               <p>When he came to his Master he made not many words, but so soon as he had supt on Sunday at night, he went to his Chamber, and laid him down upon his Bed, making no creature in the house privy to his intent, not his own Brother, his mind still running on his fair Mistriss, and the happy hour that will tye them both in one: never was there hunger-starved man that did long more for the sweet approach of wholesome food, than did <hi>Crispine</hi> for two a Clock. And so soon as the silent night had drawn all things to rest, <hi>Crispine</hi> got him up, and to <hi>Canterbury</hi> goes he to meet his Rose cheeked Lady in her Fathers Park, who also took hold of times forelock &amp; like clear <hi>Cynthia</hi> shaped her course to seek out <hi>Sol</hi> in the Meridian: But so soon as her searching eye had spied him, she commended his vigilancy, saying: He well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served his hour: <hi>O my dear</hi> (quoth he) <hi>rich Pearls do make true men thieves: But finding thee here so happily, I will fetch the Fryer straight:</hi> He had no sooner called at the Fryer door but he presently heard him, and groping the way down, he opened the door, and along they went together: but the Fryer finding his journey longer than he expected, said: that either St. <hi>Gregories</hi> Chappel was removed, or else he was not so good a foot-man as he was wont to be: <hi>That is likely enough</hi> (said <hi>Cris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine</hi>) <hi>for how much the older you are since you went this way last so much the weaker you are to travel: but be you content now, we are at the last come to the place; and therefore good Fryer make what speed you may: I warrant you</hi> (quoth he) and therewithal he puts his Spectacles upon his Nose? The fair Princess seeing that, laughed heartily, saying, <hi>Little need hath a blind man of pair of Spectacles; Truly Mistriss</hi> (said he) <hi>as little need hath an old man of a young wife: but you may see what use is: Though I be blind and cannot see a Letter, yet I cannot say Mass with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my Book and my Spectacles:</hi> and then he proceeded to solemnize their Marriage: which being finished, the Fryer had his Gold, and home he was led: In the mean time the Princess stayed still in the Park for her Bridegroom, where when he came, on a bank of sweet Primroses he pluckt the Rose of amorous delight: and after the Princess came to her Fathers Palace, and <hi>Crispine</hi> to his Masters Shop.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CAHP. VII. How <hi>Crispianus</hi> was prest to the wars, and how he fought with <hi>Iphicratis</hi> the renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed General of the <hi>Persians,</hi> who made War upon the French-men; Shewing also the occasion that a Shoomakers Son is said to be a Prince born.</head>
               <p>IN the mean time that <hi>Crispine</hi> was secretly buffed about his Marriage, his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Crispianus</hi> the same night, with many others, was prest to Wars into the Country of <hi>Gauls,</hi> now called <hi>France;</hi> which made his Master and Dame full of woe: who had committed to his Government the whole rule of his house. And when <hi>Cris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine</hi> came home, they fold him what chance had happened, and demanded where he had been: they said, they were glad he had so well escaped.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:99084:15"/>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Crispines</hi> excusing himself as well as he could, said: He was sorry for his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers sudden departure: notwithstanding the joy of his late Marriage mitigated much of his sorrow: to whom in his Brothers absence his Master gave the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight of his houshold: which place he guided with such discretion, as thereby he got both the good will of his Master, and the love of the houshold: And as he sat one day at his work he sung this song in commendation of his Marriage; himself sung the Dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and his fellows bore the Burthen.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg type="song">
                     <lg>
                        <l>AMongst the joys on Earth, though little joy there be,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey down down a down, fine is the silken Twist;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Among the married sort, much comfort I do see,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey down down a down, believe it they that list:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>He that is a married man, hath beauty to embrace,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey down down a down, and therefore mukle w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He liveth in delight, and is in happy case:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hey down down a down, in faith we think not so:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>His Wife doth dress his meat, with every thing most meet,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey down down a down, fair women love good chear;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And when he comes to bed, she gives him kisses sweet,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey down down a down, for thanks he pay full dear.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A hundred honey sweets he hath when that is done,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey down down a down, the truth is seldom known:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>He hath in little time a Daughter or a Son,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey down down a down, God grant they be his own,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>A Wife is evermore both faithful, true, and just,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey down down a down, 'tis more than you do know.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Her Husband may be sure in her to put his trust,</l>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:99084:15"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey down down a down, most are deceived so,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>While he doth ride abroad, she looks unto his house,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey down down a down, the finest cloth is torn;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And when that he comes home, she gives him Brawn and Sowse,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>hey down down a down, and oftentimes the Horn.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>How now, what is that you say</hi> (quoth <hi>Crispine</hi>)? <hi>Nothing</hi> (quoth they) <hi>but only bear the burthen of your Song: and surely we think it great pity that you are not Married, seeing you can sing so well in the praise of Marriage: Truly</hi> (quoth he) <hi>were it not for that holy institution, what would the world be, but abrood of hapless Bastards: like to the cursed seed of</hi> Cain, <hi>men fit for all manner of villany, and such as would leave behind them a race of runagate persons, that would live as badly as they are lewdly begotten.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The rest of the Iourney-men hearing him enter into such a deep discourse in the matter, began therefore to demand many questions: but seeing it appertaineth not to our matter, we will leave them to their disputation, and in the mean space I will shew you something of <hi>Crispianus,</hi> who is now in <hi>France</hi> with many noble <hi>Brittains,</hi> whom <hi>Maximinus</hi> sent thither to aid the <hi>Gauls,</hi> against the mighty force of <hi>Iphicratis</hi> the <hi>Persian</hi> General, that at this time invaded their country with a great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. The day of Battle being appointed, the Armies met in the field, at which time both the Generals like two Lyons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ed with wrath, in their proud march, viewed one another, breathing forth on both sides words of disdain, and thus the General of the <hi>Gauls</hi> began.</p>
               <p>Thou insulting Commander of the Eastern Troops, how durst thou set thy am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious foot within our Territories? Cannot the confines of <hi>Persia</hi> content thee, nor those conquered Kingdoms already in thy hand, but with unsatiable desire thou must come to usurp our right? Know thou that the undaunted <hi>Gaul</hi> do scorn thee; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit that <hi>Alexander</hi>-like thou seekest to subdue the whole world, flattering thy self in thy fortune; yet never think that the Son of a Shoomaker shall bend our neck to a servile yoak. Therefore in our just right we are come to give thee hire for thy pride: &amp; by the force of our Swords to beat down the Scepter of thy proud thoughts.</p>
               <p>The renowned <hi>Iphicratis</hi> upon these words made this reply: <hi>Now may I report that the</hi> Gauls <hi>can do something, finding them such good scolds: But know this that <hi>I</hi> come not to rail, but to revenge these contemptuous speeches and with the point of our sturdy Lances to thrust them down your throats again. Indeed my Fathers trade is a reproach to me, but thou art a reproach to thy Father; But thou shalt understand that</hi> A Shoomakers Son is a Prince born<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>▪ <hi>His Fortune made him so and thou shalt find no less.</hi> And hereupon the Trumpets sounding a charge, and the Drums striking alarum, there followed a sore and cruel fight, wherein <hi>Crispianus,</hi> like a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Hector,</hi> laid about him, hewing down his Foes on every side, whose Valiancy and Princely courage was noted of all the <hi>Gauls:</hi> and this fierce fight ended with the nights approach: each Army took their rest; at what time the Noble General of the <hi>Gauls</hi> sent for <hi>Crispianus,</hi> &amp; received him with sundry kind embracements in his Tent: he demanded of what birth he was? To whom <hi>Crispianus</hi> shaped this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer? <hi>Most worthy General, my birth is not mean, and my secrets less, but by Trade <hi>I</hi> am a Shoomaker</hi> in England.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Shoomaker</hi> (said the General) <hi>If such Fame wait upon Shoomakers, and such Magnanimity follow them, well were it for us if all the people in the Kingdom were Shoomakers: And as great thanks I am to give</hi> Maximinus, <hi>for sending me such a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99084:16"/> Souldier, as he may be proud to have such a Subject: and now right sorry am I, that ever I reproached famous</hi> Iphicratis <hi>with his Fathers trade, seeing I find it true, that Magnanimity and Knightly Prowess, is not always tyed within the compass of a noble Blood: And for my own part I will so honourably requite thy deservings, that thou shalt bless the time thou ever camest into these Wars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next morning the Generals joyned battle again, resolving in this fight, either by death, or victory, to make an end of these troubles; where the Souldiers on each side strove for the golden wreath of renown. The two Generals meeting in the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, fought couragiously together, in which bloody conflict, the Prince of the <hi>Gauls</hi> was thrice by <hi>Iphicratis</hi> unhorsed, and as many times of <hi>Crispianus</hi> mounted again: but in the end the great Commander of the Eastern Army so mightly prevailed, that he had seized on the person of the French Prince, and was carrying him Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to his Colours.</p>
               <p>But so highly was <hi>Crispianus</hi> favored of Fortune, that he and his fellows met him in the Pride of his conquest: who then all besmeared in the Persian blood, set upon <hi>Iphicratis,</hi> and so manfully behaved himself, that he recovered the Prince again, and in despight of the <hi>Persians,</hi> brought him to his royal tent; in which encounter the Noble <hi>Iphicratis</hi> was sore wounded, by reason whereof, the Souldiers had rest for three or four days: in which space, <hi>Iphicratis</hi> sent to the Prince of <hi>Gauls,</hi> to know what King he was, that in such valiant sort had rescued him out of his hands: say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That if he could serve him, he would make him Ruler of a mighty Kingdom.</p>
               <p>The French Prince sent him word, that it was a right hardy <hi>Brittain,</hi> which had performed that honourable service: but no Knight, though well deserving greater dignity; but a Shoomaker in <hi>England:</hi> and thus (quoth he) a Shoomakers Son, was by a Shoomaker foyled.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Iphicratis</hi> understood this, he sent word again to the <hi>Gauls,</hi> that for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor of that worthy man, he would not only cease the Wars, but for ever after be a friend to the <hi>Gauls:</hi> Which joyful Message when the <hi>French</hi> King understood, most willingly embraced the unlooked for Tydings of a happy peace: and thereupon made <hi>Crispianus</hi> a Knight.</p>
               <p>After the which there was a great Feast ordained, whereunto the renowned <hi>Iphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratis</hi> was invited, and the two Generals with <hi>Crispianus</hi> friendly met together: Thus the sowr War was ended with swéet feasting: and <hi>Iphicratis</hi> soon after de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted out of the Country with his Army, and never after annoyed them.</p>
               <p>Then the French King writing his Letter of thanks unto the Emperour <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus,</hi> did therein certifie him of the Princely acts of <hi>Crispianus,</hi> whereby he was brought into the Emperours favor: and with these Letters, <hi>Crispianus</hi> returned into <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. How the Lady <hi>Vrsula</hi> finding her self to be with Child, made great moan unto her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <hi>Crispine,</hi> and how he provided for her a secret place, where she was delivered.</head>
               <p>IN the mean space the Lady <hi>Ursula</hi> finding her self to be with Child, and her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Husband coming one day with shoes unto her, she made her moan unto him, saying: <hi>O</hi> Crispine <hi>how shall we do; the time of my sorrow and shame draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on, I feel that living in my womb, which I fear will bring death upon us all. Why my dear Lady</hi> (answered he) <hi>art thou with Child, keep thy chamber close, and wittily excuse thy grief, untill I have found means to procure our safety.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:99084:16"/>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <hi>But dost thou mean faithfully</hi> (said she) <hi>wilt thou not deceive me, and for fear of my Fathers wrath flye the Country? if thou shouldst do so, then were I the wretchedest Lady a live: forsake me not sweet</hi> Crispine, <hi>whatsoever thou dost, but take me with thee wheresoever thou goest; it is not my Fathers frowns that I regard, so I may have thy favour: What do I care for a Princely Palace? an homely Cottage shall content me in thy company. O my love, I will rather learn to spin Hemp for thy shop-thred, than live without thee in the greatest pleasure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will not leave thee my dear love</hi> (quoth he) <hi>by that Faith I vow, which I plighted to thee at our blessed Marriage, and therefore be contented, and it shall not be long before I return.</hi> Leaving thus his sad Lady, he came home, and secretly brake the matter unto his Dame, desiring her counsel in this his extremity</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What, how now</hi> (quoth she) <hi>hast thou got a Maid with Child? Ah thou whorson villain, thou hast undone thy self, how wilt thou do now? thou hast made a fair hand: here is now sixteen-pence a week, besides sope and candles, beds, shirts, biggings, wast-coats, head-bands, swadle-bands, cross-cloths, bibs, tail-coats, mantles, hose, shooes, coats, petticoats, cradle, and crickets, and beside that a standing-stool, and a Posnet to make the child pap, and all this is come upon thee, besides the charge of her lying in: Oh</hi> Crispine, Crispine, <hi>I am heartily sorry for thee. But in good faith, if I knew the quean that hath brought thee to this folly, I would have her by the face, I swear to you: for though I speak it before thee</hi> (Crispine) <hi>thou art a propper fellow, and thou mightest have done full well, if thou hadst had grace; God hath done his part on thee:</hi> and with that she began with kindness to weep, whereupon her Husband coming in asked what she ailed: <hi>O man</hi> (said she) Crispine: <hi>Why, what of</hi> Crispine <hi>tell me; why speakest thou not? we shall lose a good servant, so we shall. What servant shall we lose, foolish woman?</hi> quoth he, tell me quickly. <hi>O Husband, by Cock and Pye I swear I'le have her by the Nose. Who wilt thou have by the Nose? what the Devil art thou mad, that thou wilt not answer me?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Crispine,</hi> who at his Masters coming in shunned the Room, lending an ear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to these words, went to his Master, and said unto him: <hi>Sir, these four years have I served you, and the fifth draweth near unto an end: and as I have found you a good Master to me, so I trust you have had no great cause to complain of me, though through ignorance I have sometimes made offence: And knowing at this instant no man so near a friend unto me as your self, I have thought good to impart my secret counsel unto you; something I presumed upon my good Dames favour, which made
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99084:17"/> me open that unto her, which now I wish I had not discovered: Notwithstanding, rest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more upon her discretion than her secresie, I would desire your counsel in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that concerns me very near. Verily,</hi> said his Master, <hi>if it be a thing wherein I may do thee good, thou shalt find that I will not fall from thee in thy sorrows, and therefore be not abashed to declare thy mind: for I swear, if I may procure thee right, thou shalt put up no wrong. Why then Sir, thus it is</hi> (quoth he) <hi>my will running be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my wit, I have gotten a Maid with Child, and I wot not in this case what to do, that I might preserve the Maid from shame, and my self from discredit: Besides, I doubt if it be known it will cost me my life; therefore in such a case good Master be secret. Tush man, fear not</hi> (quoth he) <hi>it is a matter of nothing: but I pray thee now tell me what wanton wagtail it is that thou hast clapt under the Apron? O Master</hi> (quoth he) <hi>the Kings fair Daughter</hi> Vrsula <hi>is my love, and she it is that lives in care for my sake. Passion of my heart thou whorson Knave,</hi> quoth his Master, <hi>thou art a dead man; I marvel how the Devil thou camest to be so bold with her? Surely thou hast drawn on her Shooes on Sunday, I may say, thou hast left so good a token behind; but in truth my boy I commend thee that thou wouldst shoot at the fairest. Yea, Sir</hi> (quoth <hi>Crispine</hi>) <hi>and I have hit the mark I trow, and I do verily believe that none will shoot so near again. Nay, swear not,</hi> said his Master, <hi>many may aim at fair marks, and more than one man hits them now and then: but what wouldst thou have me to do in this case? My good Master</hi> (quoth <hi>Crispine</hi>) <hi>the truth is she is my Wife, and the very same night my Brother was prest to the Wars, I was married to her: and if you could tell me how she might be delivered of her burthen without any suspition, I should not only remain beholding to you while I live, but would also gratifie your kindness in such sort as would content you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Dame all this while listned to their talk, and when she understood he spake of the Kings Daughter, and that he had Married her, she said; <hi>Now Gods blessing on thy heart</hi> Crispine, <hi>that thou art so careful for thy Wife: but it maketh me wonder she should marry a Shoomaker, and a poor fellow too. Master and Dame</hi> (<abbr>qd</abbr>
                  <hi>Crispine</hi>) <hi>seeing I have begun, I'le shew you a further matter, as strange as the other. The ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of these times makes many noble personages to mask in this habit, as</hi> Iupiter <hi>did in a Shepherds weeds: and the truth is, the Lady</hi> Vrsula <hi>is not ignorant that by matching with me, she hath wedded a Prince; and you may say, that these five years two Princes have served you obediently, under the simple borrowed names of</hi> Crispine <hi>and</hi> Crispianus. <hi>Our Royal Father was slain by the Emperour</hi> Maximinus, <hi>and the Queen our Mother yet lies imprisoned: and your poor house, and these Leather Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have been our life of defence, against the blood-thirsty Tyrant. Now you see that though there was hate toward us in the Father, yet there is love yielded us by the Daughter. This must be kept for a certain time from the knowledge of him, lest our lives pay a dear ransome for our loves. Well</hi> Crispine (quoth his Dame) <hi>be of good chear, for I have a device in my head how to get thy Love out of her Fathers Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, that she may be brought to bed in mine own house, without either hurt to thee, or dishonour to her, if thou wilt do as I wish thee: when you do perceive that she grows near unto the time of her travel, I would wish you to work such means, as to set a Tree on fire late in the night, that standeth somewhat near one of the Beacons upon the Sea-coast, whereby it will follow, that such watch-men that watch on our Beacons, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing the Beacons upon the Sea-coast to be on fire, will set theirs on fire also. Then will there be a great hurly burly, with the preparation of men at Arms on all sides, to withstand the supposed Foe, the which they shall never find: then (as you know)</hi> Maximinus <hi>with his houshold will be in most fear, because he is most hated: that whilst
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99084:17"/> he is abroad, the rest of his houshold will every one of them seek for their own safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard, amongst the which let fair</hi> Vrsula <hi>be one, who by that means singling her self alone, may take up my house, and here she may be closely kept till she be delivered, taking upon her the name and habit of a simple woman. But the truth of this matter,</hi> (quoth <hi>Crispine</hi>) <hi>I doubt it will be soon perceived and found, then how shall Lady</hi> Vrsula <hi>do, for she will straight be missed? Tush, that is no matter,</hi> (quoth his Dame) <hi>and missed let her be, untill such time as she is in better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ase to go abroad again: so in such a tumult as then will be, they will suppose many things, that one mischance or other is befallen her; or if she be in health, that she hath wandred into the Woods, or some other uncouth place, where she might best provide for safety; and when she comes home again, I warrant thee</hi> Crispine <hi>she shall be welcome.</hi> Then said his Master, <hi>I like my Wives counsel well, therefore by my consent put it in practice:</hi> whereunto <hi>Crispine</hi> consented; and making the Lady privy to the purpose, at length it was put in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution; at which there was crying out on all sides, <hi>Arm, Arm, Arm, our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are coming upon us:</hi> Where? quoth they, at <hi>Rucupium,</hi> said one; at <hi>Aruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> Castle, said another; quoth the third, it is at <hi>Doris;</hi> I tell you (quoth the fourth) it is at <hi>Dour;</hi> and all this while it is but at <hi>Dover</hi> (said the fift<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man) and at <hi>Dover</hi> it is undoubtedly, therefore haste haste away, for never was there more need: so that <hi>Maximinus</hi> was almost at his wits end, as one not knowing which way to turn, the crys of the people came so thick one after another: The waiting Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women left the Princess, and sought for their own safety: Thus while some were busie in carrying out the Kings Treasure, others hiding the Plate, and others the Goods, <hi>Ursula</hi> had an easie passage into the Shoomakers house.</p>
               <p>The young Prince <hi>Crispine,</hi> was gone with the rest of the Town towards <hi>Dover,</hi> where when they came there was nothing to do: which when <hi>Maximinus</hi> saw, he was not a little glad the wars were so soon ended: But when he came to the Court and missed his Daughter, there was posting up and down in every place to séek her, but all in vain, for no man could meet with her, for which he made great lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, making a Proclamation throughtout the whole Countrey, <hi>That whatsoever could bring her to him, he should not only have a Princely reward, but also if he were a man of Noble blood, he should be honoured with the Marriage of his fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Daughter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was good news to <hi>Crispine,</hi> who was not to learn to make profit thereof: But by that time the Lady was light, <hi>Crispianus</hi> his eldest brother arrived in <hi>England,</hi> with great Honour, as before you have heard. And before he went to the Court, he thought it good to visit his old Master, who came also in good time to the Christening of his Brothers Child, which when he with wonder beheld, noting what a strange accident there was, that <hi>Maximinus</hi>'s Daughter should be his Brothers Wife: But after that he had in Princely manner saluted the new delivered Lady, taking the Infant in his arms, he kissed it, saying: <hi>Now will I say an swear</hi> (quoth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e) <hi>that</hi> A Shoemakers Son is a Prince born: joyning in the opinion of <hi>Iphicratis,</hi> and henceforth Shoomakers shall never let their term dye.</p>
               <p>Then turning to his Master and Dame, he said; <hi>How much dear Master and Dame, are we bound to your favours, that have maintained our Honours with our Happiness, for by this means I hope we shall make a joyful conclusion of our sorrowful beginning, and I will so work, that the Emperor shall confirm what is already begun; I mean, the Honour due to these Princely Lovers, and together with our happy fortunes procure our Mothers liberty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon within a short time after he made preparation to the Court, he attired
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99084:18"/> himself in Princely manner, and with a most Knightly grace, he delivered to <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus</hi> the King of <hi>Gauls</hi> Letter; where he certified the Emperour of the Honourable Deeds performed by <hi>Crispianus,</hi> whereupon he received him to great favour, and said unto him, <hi>Right Renowned Knight, for the great honour thou hast done me in</hi> France, <hi>I will honour thee with any thing thou shalt command, that standeth with the Majesty and credit of an Emperor to give. Then I beseech your Highness</hi> (quoth he) <hi>to grant me the life and liberty of my dear Mother, that Late Queen of</hi> Logria. <hi>Art thou her Son, said Maximinus? Although thy Father was my Foe, yet must I needs say he was a most couragious and War-like Prince; thy suit is granted: and once I had a daughter was worthy of thy love, but unconstant fortune hath bereft me of that bliss. But had it pleased the fair Heavens to have left her to me this day, I would have made thee more honourable by her match; but seeing my wishing doth nothing profit thee, take hence the richest Jewel that I have, and be thou next my self in authority.</hi> With that he took from his own Neck a Collar of precious Diamonds, and gave it to <hi>Crispianus,</hi> saying, <hi>Be thou as fortunate as Polycrates.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CAHP. IX. How fair <hi>Vrsula</hi> came before her Father, with <hi>Crispine</hi> her Husband, who was joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully received by him, and in the end had his good will to confirm the Marriage betwixt them: whereupon there was great joy on both sides: and the Shoo-makers in honour of this happy day make a joyful Song.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>WIthin a certain space after, word was brought to the Emperor, that his Daughter was with a Shoomaker come to the Court, whereat <hi>Maximinus</hi> was stricken into a sudden joy, saying: <hi>An hononourable Shoomaker may he be that hath brought me my fair Daughter again; welcome my sweet</hi> Vrsula, <hi>and in good time welcome to thy Father, and welcome also is this happy young man that hath so fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately brought thee:</hi> and turning to <hi>Crispianus</hi> he said, <hi>Noble Sir Knight, take here my Daughter to Wife: not so dear Father</hi> (quoth she) <hi>this man hath best deserved my love, that hath preserved my life, and his wife will I be Why</hi> Vrsula, said her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>wilt thou darken the sunshine of my joy, with clouds of foul obstinacy, and yoke thy self so unequally; This man is a Prince: And this mans Son is another</hi> (quoth she) <hi>That is strenge,</hi> said the Emperor, <hi>can that Child be a Prince, whose Father is but a Shoomaker?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:99084:18"/>
               <p>Then answered <hi>Ursula, My Royal Father,</hi> A Shomakers Son is a Prince born. <hi>Most gracious Lord</hi> (quoth <hi>Crispianus</hi>) <hi>the very like sentence did I hear the Renowned</hi> Iphicratis <hi>pronounce to the King of</hi> Gauls, <hi>when he upbraided him with his birth.</hi> With that <hi>Crispines,</hi> Dame presented the Child to the Emperor, and fair <hi>Ursula</hi> was very diligent to uncover the Childs face, and held it to her Father. <hi>Why Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> (quoth he) <hi>art thou not ashamed to honour this base born brat so much? hence with the Elf:</hi> and therewithal pusht it from him, whereat his Daughters tears trickled down her Cheeks, and so kissing the Child gave it again to the woman. <hi>What</hi> (said <hi>Maximinus</hi>) <hi>dost thou love the Child so well that thou must kiss it, and weep for it; I have cause her dear Father</hi> (quoth she) <hi>for that this Childs Mother lay in my Mothers Belly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At these words the Emperor suspected something, demanded of <hi>Crispine</hi> of what Parentage he was; and then knowing that he was <hi>Crispianus</hi>'s Brother, all the controversie was ended, and their secret Marriage confirmed openly with great joy and triumph: at which time the Shoomakers in the same Town made Holiday, to whom <hi>Crispine</hi> and <hi>Crispianus</hi> sent most Princely gifts for to maintain their mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment: And ever after upon that day at night, the Shoomakers make great chear, and feasting, in remembrance of these two Princely Brethren: and because it might not be forgotten, they caused their names to be placed in the Kalender for a yearly remembrance, which you shall find in the Month of <hi>October,</hi> thrée days before the Feast of <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Jude.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <lg type="song">
                     <head>The Shoomakers Song on <hi>Crispianus</hi> Night.</head>
                     <l>TWo Princely Brethren once there were, right Sons unto a King,</l>
                     <l>Whose Father, Tyrant <hi>Maximinus</hi> to cruel death did bring:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Crispianus</hi> one was call'd the eldest of the two.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Crispine</hi> was the others name, which well had learn'd to wooe.</l>
                     <l>These Brethen then, were after fain from Fathers house to flye,</l>
                     <l>Because their Foes to spoyl their lives, in privy wait did lye;</l>
                     <l>Into a kind Shoomakers house, they suddenly stept in,</l>
                     <l>And there to learn the <hi>Gentle Craft</hi> did presently begin.</l>
                     <l>And five years space they lived so, with great content of mind,</l>
                     <l>So that the Tyrant could not tell whereas he should them find:</l>
                     <l>Though every day to Court they came, with Shooes for Ladies feet</l>
                     <l>They were not known by their attire, they us'd themselves so meet.</l>
                     <l>At length unto the furious Wars, was <hi>Crispianus</hi> Prest,</l>
                     <l>Whereas his Knightly prowess then, he try'd above the rest;</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Crispine</hi> found him better sport, would I had <hi>Crispine</hi> been,</l>
                     <l>The Kings fair Daughter lov'd him well, as it was after seen:</l>
                     <l>The length of this fair Ladies foot so well did <hi>Crispine</hi> know,</l>
                     <l>That none but he could please her mind, the certain truth is so:</l>
                     <l>Came he by night or else by day, he was most welcome still,</l>
                     <l>With kisses sweet she did him pay, and thanks for his good will.</l>
                     <l>So oft these Lovers twain did meet, by day and eke by night,</l>
                     <l>That at the last the Lady said she should be shamed quite:</l>
                     <l>What was the matter, tell me true, that so her sorrow bred.</l>
                     <l>Her Shoomaker most daintily, had got her Maider-head.</l>
                     <l>But at the length so wisely wrought, as doth the story tell;</l>
                     <l>Her Fathers right good will he got, and every thing was well,</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:99084:19"/>
                     <l>And <hi>Crispianus</hi> came again from Wars Victoriously;</l>
                     <l>Then Shoomakers make Holiday, and therefore so will I;</l>
                     <l>And now for <hi>Crispianus</hi> sake, this Wine I drink to thee,</l>
                     <l>And he that doth his mark mistake, and will not now pledge me,</l>
                     <l>He is not <hi>Crispianus</hi> friend, nor worthy well I wot,</l>
                     <l>To have a Lady to his Love, as <hi>Crispine</hi> he hath got.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. How Sir <hi>Simon Eyer</hi> being at first a Shoomaker, became in the end Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> through the Counsel of his Wife: And how he broke his fast every day on a Table that he said he would not sell for a thousand pounds: And how he builded <hi>Leaden-Hall.</hi>
               </head>
               <figure/>
               <p>OVr <hi>English</hi> Chronicles do make mention, that sometime there was in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable City of <hi>London,</hi> a worthy Mayor, known by the name of Sir <hi>Simon Ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> whose fame liveth in the mouth of many men to this day, who albeit he descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from mean Parentage, yet by Gods blessing in the end he came to be a most worthy man in the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>This man being brought young out of the North-Country, was bound Prentice to a Shoo-maker, bearing then the name of the <hi>Gentle-Craft</hi> (as still it doth) his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster being a man of reasonable wealth, set many Iourney-men and Prentices to work, who followed their business with great delight, which quite excludeth all weariness; for when servants do sit at their work like dromedaries, then their minds are never lightly on their business: for it is an old Proverb;
<q>
                     <lg type="proverb">
                        <l>They prove Servants kind and good,</l>
                        <l>That sing at their business like Birds in a Wood.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Such Fellows had this young Lad, who was not behind with many Northern Iigs, to answer their Southern Songs: This youth being the youngest Prentice in the House, as occasion served, was often sent to the Conduit for water, whereby in a short time he fell acquainted with many other Printices, coming thither for the same intent.</p>
               <p>Now their custome was, that every Sunday morning, divers of these Prentices did use to go to a place near the Conduit, to break their fast with Pudding Pies, and often they would take <hi>Simon</hi> along with them; but upon a time it fell out, that when
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99084:19"/> he should draw money to pay the shot with the rest, that he had none, whereupon he merrily said unto them: <hi>My faithful Friends, and Conduit-Companions, treasurers of the Water-Tankard, and main Pillars of the Pudding-house; I may now compare my Purse to a barren Doe, that yields the Keeper no more good than an empty Carcass: or to a bad Nut, which being opened hath never a Kernel: Therefore if it will please you to pardon me at this time, and excuse me for my part of the shot, I do here vow unto you, that if ever I come to be Lord Major of the City, I will give a breakfast to all the Prentices in</hi> London. <hi>We do take your word,</hi> (quoth they) and so they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</p>
               <p>It came to pass that, <hi>Simon</hi> having at length worn out the time of his Prentice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, that he fell in love with a Maiden that was near Neighbour unto him, unto whom at length he was married and got him a Shop, and laboured hard daily, and his young wife was never idle, but straight when she had nothing to do, she sat in- the Shop and spun, and having lived thus alone a year or thereabout, and having-gathered something together, at length he got him some Prentices, and a Iourney-man or two, and he could not make his ware so fast as he could have sold it, so that he stood in great néed of a Iourney-man or two more.</p>
               <p>At last one of his servants espying one go along the street with a tardle at his back, called to his Master, suying: <hi>Sir, yonder goes St.</hi> Hugh's <hi>bones, twenty pound to a penny: Run presently</hi> (quoth he) <hi>and fetch him hither:</hi> The Boy running forth cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the man, saying: <hi>Good fellow come hither, here is one would speak with you</hi> The fellow being a <hi>French-man</hi> that had not long been in <hi>England,</hi> turning about, said: <hi>Hea, what you see? will you speak wed me? Hea, what you have? tell me what you have Hea?</hi> And with that coming to the Stall, the good man askt him if he lackt work, <hi>we permasoy</hi> quoth the <hi>French-man</hi> Hereupon <hi>Simon</hi> took him in, and to work he went merrily, where he behaved himself so well, that his Master made a good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of him, thinking he had been a Batchelor, but in the end it was found other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise.</p>
               <p>This man was the first that wrought upon the low cut shooe, with the square toe. and the latchet overthwart the instep; before which time, in <hi>England</hi> they did wear a high shooe that reached above the Ankles, right after the manner of our husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens-shooes at this day, save only that it was made very sharp at the toe, turning up like the tail of an Island Dog; or as you see a Cock carry his hinder feathers.</p>
               <p>Now it is to be remembred, that while <hi>John Denevale</hi> dwelt with <hi>Simon Eyer,</hi> it chanced that a Ship of the Isle of <hi>Candy,</hi> was driven upon our Coast, laden with all kind of Lawns and Cambricks, and other Linnen Cloath, which commodities at that time were in <hi>London</hi> very scant and exceeding dear, and by reason of a great leak the Ship had got at Sea, being unable to sail any further, he would make what profit he could of his goods here.</p>
               <p>And being come to <hi>London</hi> it was <hi>John Denevales</hi> chance to meet him in the streets, of whom the Merchant in the Greek tongue, demanded where he might have a lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for be was one that had never been in <hi>England</hi> before, and being unacquainted, wist not whither to go, but while he spake Greek, <hi>John Denevele</hi> asnwered him still in French, which tongue the Merchant understood well: And therefore being glad that he had met with one that could talk with him, he declared unto him what tempests he endured at Sea and also how his Ship lay upon the Coast, with such Commodities as he would sell: <hi>Truly Sir</hi> (quoth <hi>John) I am my self but a stranger in this Country, and utterly unacquainted with Merchants, but I dwell with one in the City, that is a very honest man, and it may be that he can help you to some that will deal with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99084:20"/> you for it, and if you think it good, I will move him with it, and in the mean space I'le bring you where you may have a very good lodging; to morrow morning I will come to you again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir,</hi> said ths Merchant, <hi>if you please to do me that favour I'le not only be thankful unto you for the same, but also in most honest sort will content you for your pains:</hi> and with that they departed.</p>
               <p>Now so soon as <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Frenchman</hi> came home, he moved that matter unto his Master, desiring him that he would do what he could for the Merchant. When his Master had heard each circumstance, noting therewith the want of such commodities in the Land, he cast in his mind as he stood cutting out his work, what was the best to be done in this case, saying to his man <hi>John, I will think upon it betwixt this and the morning, and then I will tell you my mind;</hi> and therewithal casting down his cutting knife, he went out of his Shop into his Chamber, and therein walking up and down alone very sadly, ruminating hereon: he was so far in his muse, that his Wife sending for him to supper two or three times, he nothing regarded the Maids call, hammering this matter in his Head; at last his Wife came to him, saying: <hi>Husband, what mean you that you do not come to supper? Why speak you not man? hear you? good Husband come away, your meat will be cold:</hi> but for all her words he stayed walking up and down still like a man that had sent his wits a Woolgathering, which his wife seeing, pulled him by the sleeve, saying; <hi>Why Husband, in the name of God, why come you not, will you not come to supper to night? I called you a good while ago: Body of me, Wife, I promise thee I did not hear thee: No Faith, it seemeth so</hi> (quoth she) <hi>I marvel whereupon your mind runneth: Believe me Wife</hi> (quoth he) <hi>I was studying how to make my self Lord Mayor, and thee a Lady.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now God help you</hi> (quoth she) <hi>I pray God make us able to pay every man his own, that we may live out of debt and danger, and drive the Woolf from the door, and I desire no more. But Wife,</hi> said he, <hi>I pray thee now tell me, dost thou not think that thou couldst make a shift to bear the name of a Lady, if it be put upon thee? In truth Husband</hi> (quoth she) <hi>I'le not dissemble with you, if your wealth were able to bear it, my mind will bear it well enough. Well Wife,</hi> replyed he, <hi>I tell thee now in sadness, that if I had money, there is a commodity now to be bought, the gains whereof would be able to make thee a Gentlewoman for ever. Alas Husband, that dignity your Trade allows you already, being a Squire of the</hi> Gentle-Craft, <hi>then how can you be less than a Gentleman, seeing your Son is a Prince born? Tush Wife,</hi> quoth he, <hi>those Titles do only rest in Name, but not in nature: but of that sort I had rather be, whose Lands are answerable to their Virtues, and whose Rents can maintain the greatness of their mind. Then sweet Husband tell me,</hi> said his Wife, <hi>tell me what commodity is that which you might get so much by? I am sure your self hath some Money, and it shall go very hard but I'le procure friends to borrow one forty shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; and beside that, rather than you shall lose so good a bargain, I have a couple of Crowns that saw no Sun since we were first Married, and them also shall you have. Alas Wife,</hi> (said <hi>Simon) all this comes not near the matter; I confess it would do some good in buying some backs of Leather, but in this thing 'tis nothing, for this is Merchandize that is precious at this time, and rare to be had: and <hi>I</hi> hear, that whosoever will have it, must lay down three hundred pounds ready Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: Yea Wife, and yet thereby he might get three and three thousand pounds profit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His wife hearing him say so, was inflamed with the desire thereof, as women are for the most part very covetous: That matter running still in her mind, she could
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99084:20"/> scant find in her heart to spare him time to go to supper, for very eagerness to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate him on to take that Bargain upon him: Wherefore so soon as they had supt and given God thanks, she called her husband, saying: I pray you come hither, I would speak a word with you: That man is not always to be blamed, that sometimes takes counsel of his Wife, though Womens Wits are not able to comprehend the greatest things, yet in doubtful matters they oft help on a sudden.</p>
               <p>Well Wife, what mean you by this; (said her husband) In truth, quoth she, <hi>I</hi> would have you to pluck up a mans heart, &amp; speedily chop up a bargain for these goods you speak of. VVho <hi>I,</hi> quoth he, which way should I do it? that am not able for three thousand pounds to lay down three thousand pence? Tush man, quoth she, what of that? every man that beholds a man in the face, knows not what he hath in his purse: and whatsoever he be that ows the goods, he will no doubt be content to stay a month for his money, or three weeks at the least: and I promise you, to pay a thousand pounds a week is a pretty round payment, and I may say to you, not much to be misliked of.</p>
               <p>Now husband, I would have you in the morning, with <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Frenchman</hi> go to the Grecian Merchant, and with good discretion drive a sound bargain with him for the whole fraight of the Sip, and thereupon give him half a douzen Angels in earnest, and eight and twenty days after the delivery of the goods, condition to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him the rest of his money: But woman (quoth he) dost thou imagine that he will take my word upon so weighty a mass of money, and to deliver his goods upon no better security;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Good Lord,</hi> quoth she, <hi>have you not wit in such a case to make shift; I'le tell you what you shall do: Be not known that you bargain for your own self, but tell him that you do it in the behalf of one of the chief Alderman in the City: but beware in any case that you leave with him your name in writing, he being a</hi> Grecian <hi>cannot read</hi> English, <hi>and you have no need at all to shew</hi> Iohn <hi>the</hi> Frenchman, <hi>or if you should, it were no matter, for you can tell well enough, that he can neither write nor read.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I perceive Wife,</hi> quoth he, <hi>thou woulst fain be a Lady, and worthy thou art to be one, that dost thus imploy thy Wits to bring thy Husband profit: but tell me, if he should be desirous to see the Alderman to confer with him, how shall we do then:</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus <hi>have mercy upon us,</hi> quoth she, <hi>you say women are fools, but me seemeth men have need to be taught sometimes: Before you come away in the morning, let</hi> Iohn <hi>the</hi> Frenchman <hi>tell him, that the Alderman himself shall come to his Lodging in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, and receiving a note of all the goods that be in the Ship, he shall deliver unto him a Bill of his Hand for the payment of his money, according to that time. Now sweet-heart,</hi> quoth she, <hi>this Alderman shall be thine own self, and I'le go bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for thee all things that shall be necessary, against that time. Tush,</hi> quoth her Husband, <hi>canst thou imagine that he seeing me in the morning, will not know me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the afternoon; Go Husband,</hi> quoth she, <hi>he will not know thee I warrant thee: for in the morning thou shalt go to him in thy doublet of Sheeps-skin, with a smutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed face, and thy Apron before thee, thy Thumb-leather and Hand-leather buckled close to thy wrist, with a foul Band about thy Neck, and a greasie cap on thy Head. Why Woman,</hi> quoth he, <hi>to go in such sort would be a discredit to me, and make the Merchant doubtful of my dealing: for men of simple attire, are (God wot) slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly esteemed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hold your peace good Husband,</hi> quoth she, <hi>it shall not be so with you, for</hi> Iohn <hi>the</hi> Frenchman <hi>shall give such good report to the Merchant for your honest dealing (as</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:99084:21"/> I praise God, he can do no less) as the Grecian will rather conceive the better of you, than otherwise, judging you a prudent and discreet man, that will not make a shew of that you are not, but go in your attire agreeable to your trade. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause none of our folks shall be privy to our intent, to morrow we will dine at my Couzin <hi>John Barbers,</hi> in St. <hi>Clements</hi> Lane, which is not far from the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Lumbard-street,</hi> where the Merchant stranger lies. Now I'le be sure that all things shall be ready at my Couzin <hi>John's,</hi> that you may put on in the afternoon. And there he shall first of all with his Scissers, snap off all the superfluous Hairs and fashion thy bruishy Beard after the Aldermans grave cut: then shall he wash thee with a sweet Camphire Ball, and besprinkle thy head and face with the purest Rose-water: then shalt thou scour thy pitchy fingers in a Bason of hot water, with an ordinary Washing-Ball: And all this being done, strip thee from these common weeds, &amp; I'le put thee on a very fair doublet of tauny Satten, over which thou shalt have a Cas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sock of branched Damask, furred round the skirts with the finest foyns, thy Breech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of black Velvet, and Shooes and stockings fit for such array; a band about thy neck as white as the driven snow, and for thy wrists a pretty pair of cuffs and on thy head a cap of the finest black: then shalt thou put on a fair Gown, wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed about with Velvet, and overthwart thy back, thwart it shall be with rich foyns, with a pair of sweet Gloves on thy hands, and on thy fore-finger a great Seal Ring of Gold.</p>
               <p>Thou being thus attired, I'le intreat my Couzin <hi>John Barber</hi> because he is a very handsome young-man, neat and fine in his apparel, as indeed all Barbers are, that he would take the pains to wait upon you unto the Merchant, as if he were your man, which he will do at the first, because one of you cannot understand the other, so that it will be sufficient with outward courtesie, one to greet another, and he to deliver un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you his note, and you to give him your Bill, and so to come home.</p>
               <p>It doth my heart good to see how trimly this apparel doth become you, in faith Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, me seem in my mind I see you in it already, &amp; how like an Alderman you will look when you are in this costly array. At your return home from the Marchant, you shall put off all these cloaths at my Couzins again, and come home as you did go forth: then tell <hi>John</hi> the Frenchman, that the Alderman was with the Merchant this after-noon, you may send to him in the morning, &amp; bid him to command that his Ship may be brought down the River: while she is coming about you may give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to the Linnen-Drapers of the Commodities you have coming. Enough Wife, quoth he, thou hast said enough; and by the grace of God I'le follow thy counsel, and I doubt not but to have good fortune,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CAHP. XI. How <hi>Simon Eyer</hi> was sent for to my Lord Mayors to Supper, and shewing the great entertainment he and his Wife had there.</head>
               <p>ANon after Supper time drew near, she making her self ready in the best man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner she could devise, passed along with her Husband unto my Lord Mayors House; and being entred the great Hall, one of the Officers certified my Lord Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yor, that the great rich Shoomaker and his Wife were already come. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Lord Mayor in courteous manner came into the Hall to <hi>Simon,</hi> saying: You are most heartily welcome good Master <hi>Eyer,</hi> and so is your gentle bed-fellow: Then came the Lady Mayoress and saluted them both in like manner, saying: Welcome good Master <hi>Eyer,</hi> and Mistress <hi>Eyer</hi> both: and taking her by the hand, set her down among the Gentlewomen there present.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:99084:21"/>
               <figure/>
               <p>Sir, quoth the Lord Mayor, I understand you are a Shoomaker, and that it is you that have bought all the goods of the great Argozy. I am indeed, my Lord, of the Gentle-Craft, quoth he, and I praise God, all the goods of the great Argozy are mine own, when my debts are paid.</p>
               <p>God give you much joy of them, said the Lord Mayor, and I trust you and I shall deal for some part thereof. So the meat being then ready to be brought in, the Guests were placed, each one according to their calling. My Lord Mayor holding <hi>Simon</hi> by the Hand, and the Lady Mayoress holding his Wife, they néeds would have them sit near to themselves, which they then with blushing cheeks refusing, my Lord said unto them, holding his cap in his hand:</p>
               <p>Master <hi>Eyer,</hi> and Mistriss <hi>Eyer,</hi> let me intreat you not to be troublesome, for I tell you it shall be thus: and as for these Gentlemen here present, they are all of mine own acquaintance, and many times we have been together, therefore I dare be the bolder with them, and albeit you are our neighbours also, yet I promise you, you are strangers to my Table: and to strangers, common courtesie doth teach us to shew the greatest favour, therefore let me rule you in my own House, and you shall rule me in yours.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Simon</hi> found there was no remedy, they sat them down, but the poor Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was so abashed, that she did eat but little meat at the Table, behaving her self at the Table with a comely and modest countenance, but what she wanted in outward feeding, her Heart yielded to her with inward delight and content.</p>
               <p>Now so it was, many men that knew not <hi>Simon,</hi> and seeing him in so simple attire sit next my Lord, whisperingly asked one another what he was: and it was enough for <hi>Simon's</hi> Wife, with her eyes and ears, to see and hearken after every thing that was said or done.</p>
               <p>A grave wealthy Citizen sitting at the Table, spake to <hi>Simon,</hi> and said: Sir, in good will I drink to your good health, but I beseech you pardon me, for I know not how to call your name. With that my Lord Mayor answered him saying: His name is Master <hi>Eyer,</hi> and this is the Gentleman that bought all the goods that came in the <hi>Black Swan of Candy,</hi> and before God, though he sit here in simple sort, for his wealth, I do verily believe, he is more sufficient to bear this place than my self: this was a man that was never thought upon, living obscure amongst us, of none account in the eyes of the World, carrying the countenance but of a Shoomaker, and none of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99084:22"/> best neither, and is able to deal for a bargain of five thousand pounds at a clap. We do want many such Shoomakers (said the Citizen) and so with other discourse drove out Supper: at what time rising from the Table, <hi>Simon</hi> and his Wife receiving sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry salutations of my Lord Mayor and his Lady, and all the rest of the Worshipful guests, departed home to their own house, at what time his Wife made such a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cital of the matters, how bravely they were entertained, what great chear was there, also what a great company of Gentlemen and Gentlewomen were there, and how often they drank to her Husband and to her, with divers other circumstances, that <hi>I</hi> believe that if the night had béen six months long, as it is under the North pole, they would have found talk enough till morning. Of a truth, quoth she, although I sat close by my Ladies side, I could eat nothing for very joy to hear and sée that we were so much made of: And never give me credit husband, if <hi>I</hi> did not hear the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers whisper as they stood behind me, &amp; all demanded one of another what you were and what I was: O, quoth one, do you sée this man? mark him well, and mark his Wife well, that simple Woman that sits next my Lady, what are they? what are they? quoth another: Marry this is the rich Shoomaker that bought all the goods in the great <hi>Argozy;</hi> I tell you there was never such a Shoomaker séen in <hi>London</hi> since the City was builded.</p>
               <p>Now by my faith, quoth the third, <hi>I</hi> have heard much of him to day among the Merchants in the stréets, going betwéen the two Chains. Credit me Husband, of mine honesty, this was their communication. Nay, &amp; do you not remember when the rich Citizen drank to you (which craved pardon because he knew not your name) what my Lord Mayor said: Sir, quoth he, his name is Master <hi>Ever:</hi> did you mark that? and presently thereupon he added these words: This is the Gentleman that bought, &amp; so forth: The Gentleman understood you: did you hear him speak that word?</p>
               <p>In troth Wife, quoth he, my Lord uttered many good words of me, <hi>I</hi> thank his honour, but <hi>I</hi> heard not that. No, quoth she, <hi>I</hi> heard it well enough, for by and by he procéeded further, saying: I suppose though he sit here in simple sort, he is more sufficient to bear this charge than my self. Yea, though <hi>I,</hi> he may thank his Wife for that, if it come to pass. Nay, said <hi>Simon,</hi> I thank God for it. Yea, and next him, you may thank me, quoth she: And it did her so much good to talk of it, that I suppose if she had lived till this day, she would yet be prating thereof, and if sleep did not drive her from it.</p>
               <p>And now seeing that <hi>Simon</hi> the Shoomaker is become a Merchant, we will tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per our tongue to give him the Title which his customers were wont to do, and from henceforth call him Master <hi>Eyer,</hi> who while he had his affairs in hand, committed the government of his shop to <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Frenchman,</hi> leaving him to be guide to his other Servants; by means of which favour, <hi>John</hi> thought himself at that time to be a man of no small reputation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:99084:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. How <hi>Iohn</hi> the Frenchman fell in love with one of his Mistrisses Maids, and how he was crossed through the craft of <hi>Haunce</hi> the Dutchman.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>AT the same time there was dwelling in the House a jolly Wench, whose name was <hi>Florence,</hi> whom <hi>John</hi> the Frenchman loved dearly well, and for her only sake he brought many a good Bottle of Wine into the House, &amp; therewithal so soon as their Master and Mistriss were gone to bed, they would oftentimes make merry amongst themselves, which <hi>Haunce</hi> a Iourney-man in the same House perceiving, sought to crose him as much as in him lay, thereby to bring his own purpose the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to pass, which was to joyn the Maidens favours to his own affections.</p>
               <p>And because the Frenchman had the greatest gains under his Master, and being thereof no niggard when he had got it, the Maid did most delight in him, and little estéemed the Dutchman, though his good will was as great towards her as the other: for they could not be in any corner of the House together, nor could they meet in any place abroad, but the Dutchman would still watch them.</p>
               <p>Vpon a time <hi>Florence</hi> being at Market, her Love <hi>John</hi> went forth of the Shop to meet her, and <hi>Haunce</hi> stayed not long behind, who at length espyed them, and heard his fellow <hi>John</hi> questioning with her in this sort:</p>
               <p>What <hi>Florence,</hi> what have you in your Basket? hea, let me see what you buy, Marry <hi>John,</hi> quoth she, I have bought Beef &amp; Mutton, &amp; other things: Come, come must you péep in my Basket, quoth she, away for shame, away. Be Cot <hi>Florence,</hi> me will see a little, ha, ha! <hi>Florence,</hi> you buy de pudding: hea, you love de puddings <hi>Florence,</hi> hea? Yea Sir, quoth she, what if <hi>I</hi> do love pudding, what care you: of my tra <hi>Florence,</hi> if <hi>I</hi> be your husband, me will give you pudding shall warren. My husband, quoth she, in faith Sir, no, <hi>I</hi> mean not to marry a Frenchman: What <hi>Florence,</hi> de Frenchman be de good man: but <hi>Flor.</hi> me will give you a point of wine by me treat.</p>
               <p>O <hi>I</hi> cannot stay now, <hi>I</hi> thank you <hi>John.</hi> What, quoth he, <hi>Florence,</hi> no stay with your friend, <hi>I</hi> shall make you stay a little time: &amp; so with that, taking her by the hand, into the Tavern they go,; and <hi>Haunce</hi> the Dutchman following them, sat closely in the next room, &amp; by that means he heard all that they said, and that they appointed the next Sunday to go to <hi>Islinton</hi> together, and there to be merry, and so the Maid hasting away, they departed.</p>
               <p>Well, quoth <hi>Haunce</hi> secretly to himself, it shall go hard but I'le disappoint you,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99084:23"/> Sunday in the afternoon being come, <hi>John</hi> the Frenchman, according to his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, went before to <hi>Islington,</hi> leaving <hi>Florence</hi> to come after with another Maid, which dwelt in the same House, whilst he prepared good chear for their coming; and the more to make her merry, he hired a noise of Musicians to attend their pleasure.</p>
               <p>And as it after hapned, his fellow <hi>Haunce</hi> prevented this sport, who watching in the Fields for <hi>Florence,</hi> at length he spyed her coming: to whom he said, Well met fair <hi>Florence,</hi> your friend <hi>John</hi> hath changed his mind, for whereas he appointed you to meet him at <hi>Islington,</hi> you shall lose your labour so to do, for he is not there. No, how so; said <hi>Florence.</hi> The reason is, said <hi>Haunce,</hi> so far as I can understand by him, he thinks you are very fickle and unconstant, and because it was his chance this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to see you speak to a young man that passed by, he saith verily, that you are a marvellous great dissembler, and in this humour he is gone I know not whither.</p>
               <p>And is it even so, said <hi>Florence:</hi> I'le tell thee what <hi>Haunce,</hi> because he hath made thee privy to his mind, I will shew thée somewhat of mine: Doth he suspect me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I did but speak to one: Nay, if he be so jealous now, what will he be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? and therefore insomuch as it is so, let him go to the Devil, he shall very well find that I will set as light by him as he doth by me. Did the Knave get leave of my Mistriss for me to come abroad this day, and doth he now serve me thus? Well, this shall teach me Wit in faith, and so she turns back again.</p>
               <p>Nay, <abbr>qd</abbr>
                  <hi>Haunce,</hi> seeing now you are abroad, let me intreat you to go to <hi>Hogsden,</hi> and I will bestow a mess of Cream upon you. In the end she was won, and as they walked together, <hi>Haunce</hi> spoke thus unto her: I know not what cause <hi>John</hi> the Frenchman hath given you to bear him so good will, as I perceive you do, but in my mind he is a far unméet match for you. And thus much I know, he is of a very mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strustful nature, a wavering mind, and deceitful heart: he did profess great good, will to you in outward shew, but I have heard him speak most shamefully of you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind your back, making his vaunts that he had you at a beck of his finger and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow that for a pint of Wine he could cause you to follow him up and down all over the City: <hi>Florence,</hi> I am a fool to tell you thus much, it may be you will scarce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, and for my part I will not urge you thereunto: but in troth, look what I tell you, it is for good will, because I have been sorry to sée you abused.</p>
               <p>I thank you good <hi>Haunce,</hi> quoth she, I may believe it well enough, but from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth I know what I have to do: I con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ess indéed that I have drank with him abroad, but it was at his own earnest entreaty, neither could I ever be quiet for the Knave, he doth so follow me up and down in every place: but seeing I know his dissimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be such, if I do not requite him in his kind, trust me no more and now I am heartily sorry that I was so foolish as to follow him this day at his appointment, but séeing he hath served me thus, he shall not know of my coming out of doors, and therefore good <hi>Haunce</hi> do not tell him you met me this day in the fields.</p>
               <p>Now in faith <hi>Florence</hi> (quoth he) I will not only be secret to thee, but will also from henceforth acquaint thée with all my proceedings. And having eaten their Cream, <hi>Haunce</hi> brought her some part of the way homewards; and taking his leave of her, he went back to sée if he could meet with <hi>John</hi> the Frenchman, who having stayed at <hi>Islington</hi> for <hi>Florence</hi> until almost night, and she not coming, he and the Musitians together were fain to eat up the meat without more company, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed <hi>John</hi> the Frenchman to swear like a Turk.</p>
               <p>And as he was coming homeward over the field, chasing and fretting to himself, who should he meet withal but <hi>Haunce</hi> the Dutchman, who said to him: What <hi>John,</hi> who thought to méet you here: Here thou seest <hi>I</hi> am now said <hi>John,</hi> but when come
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:99084:23"/> you from home? Marry but even, now quoth <hi>Haunce.</hi> And who is at home, said <hi>John,</hi> The other answered, there was no body but their Mistriss, and the Maid <hi>Florence,</hi> with the rest of the Houshold? Is <hi>Florence</hi> at home, said <hi>John?</hi> the Devil take her for me, she hath made a right fool of me indeed. How so, quoth <hi>Haunce:</hi> Then the other in a great chafe said: Be Got shall revenged, <hi>Florence</hi> make on me too mush, too mush, she make me believe she love me, &amp; methink so too: and be Got she make me a Iack fool. When <hi>Haunce</hi> heard him say so, he said: Alas good <hi>John</hi> she love thee! if you think so, you are greatly deceived, for she is the scoffingest Quean in <hi>London,</hi> and I have heard her behind your back, to mock and flout you, saying: Doth shitten <hi>John</hi> think that I will Marry him, in faith Sir no▪ When the <hi>Frenchman</hi> heard this, he stampt like a mad man, and bit his thumb, saying: Mordue me shall be revenged he Got: shitten <hi>John</hi> call a shitten <hi>John,</hi> hea: Adeput in corroyn, ame shant, shitten <hi>John;</hi> no better name but shitten <hi>John?</hi> It is as I tell you, quoth <hi>Haunce:</hi> &amp; moreover, she said, she scorned to come after you to <hi>Islington,</hi> saying: she would see you hanged first. Well, be no matter, she no love me, me no love she, but me shall go home, me shall, and beat her like a Stock-fish: Nay, do not so, saith <hi>Haunce,</hi> but let her alone, for it is no credit for you to beat a Woman: and besides that, if you should, our Master would turn you out of doors, therefore be quiet a while, and be secret in that I have told you, then shall you see how she useth you.</p>
               <p>In this humour they departed, at what time <hi>John</hi> full of melancholy stood frown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the fires side, and as the Maid went up and down the House about her business, he casts looks on her as fierce as a Panther: but she by reason of the Dutchmans tale to her, shews her self as scornful as he was churlish, and not once cast her eye toward him, and thus they drove on the time for a senight or fortnight.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. How Master <hi>Eyer</hi> was called upon to be Sheriff of <hi>London,</hi> and how he held his place with Worship.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>IN this space Master <hi>Eyer</hi> following his business, had sold so much of his Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize as paid the Grecian his whole money, &amp; yet had resting to himself thrée times as much as he had sold, wherefore he frusted some of it to one Alderman and some to another, &amp; a great deal amongst substantial Merchants: &amp; for some had much ready money, which he imployed in divers Merchandizes, &amp; became adventurer at Sea ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (by Gods blessing) many prosperous voyages, so that his riches daily increased.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:99084:24"/>
               <p>It chanced upon a time, that being in his study casting up his accounts, he found himself to be clearly worth twelve or thirtéen thousand pounds: which he finding to be so, called his Wife to him, and said:</p>
               <p>The last day I did cast up my accounts, and I find that Almighty God of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, hath lent me thirtéen thousand pounds to maintain us in our old age, for which his gracious goodness towards us, let us with whole hearts give his glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty eternal praise, and therewithal pray unto him, that we may so dispose thereof, as may be to his Honour, and the Comfort of his poor members on earth, and above our Neighbors we may not be puffed up with pride, that while we think on our Wealth, we forget God that sent it us: for it hath béen an old saying of a wise man: <hi>That abundance groweth from riches, and disdain out of abundance:</hi> of which God give us grace to take heed, and grant us a contented mind.</p>
               <p>So soon as he had spoken this, he heard one hastily knocking at door, whereupon he sent <hi>Florence</hi> to sée who it was, the Maiden coming again, told her Master it was one of my Lord Mayors Officers, that would speak with him. The Officer being permitted to come in: after due reverence, he said: Sir, it hath pleased my Lord Mayor, with the Worshipful Aldermen his Brethren; with the council of the whole Commonalty of the Honourable City, to chuse your Worship Sheriff of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> this day, and have sent me to desire you to come and certifie your mind therein, whether you be contented to hold the place or no.</p>
               <p>Master <hi>Eyer</hi> hearing this, answered: he would come to his Honour, and their worships incontinent, and resolve them what he was minded to do: and so the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer departed.</p>
               <p>His Wife (which all this while listned to their talk) hearing how the case stood, with a joyful countenance méeting her Husband, taking him about the neck, with a loving kiss, said: Master Sheriff, God send thée joy of thy name and place. O Wife (<abbr>qd</abbr> he) my person is far unworthy of that place, &amp; the name far excéeds my degrée.</p>
               <p>What, content your self good Husband, quoth she, and disable not your self in such sort, but be thankful unto God for what you have, &amp; do not spurn at such promotion as God sendeth you: The Lord be praised for it, you have enough to discharge the place whereunto you are called with credit: and wherefore sendeth God goods, but therewithal to do him and your Country service? Woman (quoth he) soft fire makes sweet malt; for such as take things in hand rashly, repent it suddenly: to be Sheriff of <hi>London</hi> is no little cost. Consider first, quoth he, what house I ought to have, and what costly ornaments belong thereunto; as hangings of Tapestry, cloath of Arras, and other such like, what store of Plate, and goblets of Gold, what costly attire, and what a chargable train, and that which is most of all, how greatly I stand charged beside to our Soverain Lord the King, for answering of such prisoners as shall be committed to my custody, with a hundred matters of such importance, which are to such an Office belonging.</p>
               <p>Good Lord Husband, quoth she, what need all these repetitions? you need not tell me it is a matter of great charge: Notwithstanding, I verily think many heretofore have with great credit discharged the place, whose wealth hath not in any sort been answerable to your riches, and whose wits have been as mean as your own: Truly Sir, shall I be plain? I know not any thing that is to be spoken of, that you want to perform it, but only your good will, and to lack good will to do your King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try good, were a sign of an unworthy subject, which I hope you will never be.</p>
               <p>Well Wife (said her Husband) thou hast held me here with prittle prattle, while the time passeth on, it is high time I were gone to <hi>Guild-hall</hi> I doubt I shall appear too
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:99084:24"/>
                  <hi>unmannerly in causing my</hi> Lord Mayor, <hi>and the rest to stay my leisure.</hi> And he having made himself ready, meet to go before such an Assembly as he went unto, he went out of doors, at what time his Wife called after him, saying, and holding up her finger.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Husband, remember, you know what I have said: take heed you dissemble not with God and the world, look to it Husband: go, get you in</hi> quoth he, <hi>about your business, and so away he went.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So soon as he was gone out of sight, his Wife sent one of his men after him, to <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> to hearken and hear whether he held his place or no; <hi>And if he do, bring me word with all possible speed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will Mistriss, <hi>quoth her man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now when <hi>Mr. Eyer</hi> came to <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> the Lord Mayor &amp; his brethren had him heartily welcome, saying: <hi>Sir, the Commonalty of the City having a good opinion of you, have chosen you for one of the</hi> Sheriffs <hi>for this year, not doubting but to find you a fit man for the place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My good Lord,</hi> quoth he, <hi>I humbly thank the City for their courtesie and kindness, and would to God my wealth were answerable to my good will, and my ability were able to bear it: but I find my self insufficient: I most humbly desire a years respite more, and pardon for this present.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At these words a grave Commoner of the City standing up, with due reverence, spake thus unto the Mayor: <hi>My good Lord, this is but a slender excuse for Mr.</hi> Eyer <hi>to make, for I have often heard him say, and so have divers others also, that he hath a Table in his house, whereon he breaks his fast every day, that he will not give for a thousand pound: wherefore (under your Lordships correction) in my simple judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I think he that is able to spare a thousand pounds in such a dead chomodity, is very sufficient to be</hi> Sheriff <hi>of London.</hi> See you now, <hi>quoth my Lord,</hi> I muse Mr. <hi>Eyer, that you would have so lame an excuse before us, as to make exception at your own wealth, which is apparently proved sufficient: you must know Mr.</hi> Eyer, <hi>that the Commons of</hi> London <hi>have searching eyes, and seldom they are deceived in their opinion, and therefore look what is done, you must stand to it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I beseech you my Lord,</hi> quoth <hi>Mr. Eyer, give me leave to speak one word: Let it be granted, that I will not give my Table whereon I break my fast, for a thousand pounds, that is no consequence to prove it is worth so much, my fancy to the thing</hi> is all; for doubtless no man here would give me a thousand shillings for it, when they see it. <hi>All is one for that,</hi> quoth my Lord Mayor, <hi>yet I dare give you as much wine as you will spend this year in your</hi> Shrivalty, <hi>to let me have it: My good Lord,</hi> quoth he, <hi>on that condition I will hold my place, and rest no longer troublesome to this company. You must hold,</hi> said my Lord, <hi>without any condition or exceptions at all in this matter:</hi> And so they ended.</p>
               <p>The Assembly being then broken up, the voice went, <hi>Mr.</hi> Eyer <hi>is Sheriff, Mr.</hi> Eyer <hi>is Sheriff.</hi> Whereupon the fellow that Mistriss <hi>Eyer</hi> sent to observe how things framed, ran in all hast, and with leaping and rejoycing, said: <hi>Mistriss, God give you joy, for you are now a Gentlewoman. What,</hi> quoth she, <hi>tell me, Sir sawce, is thy Master</hi> Sheriff <hi>or no? and doth he hold his place? yea Mistriss, he holds his Place now, as fast as the Stirrup doth the Shooe while we sow it: Why then,</hi> quoth she, <hi>I have my Hearts desire, and that I so long looked for.</hi> And so away she went,</p>
               <p>Within a while after came her Husband, and with him one of the <hi>Aldermen</hi> and a couple of wealthy Commoners, one of them was be that gave such great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99084:25"/> of his Table: and coming to his door, he said: <hi>You are welcome home good Master Sheriff. Nay, I pray you come in and drink with me before you go.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then said he, <hi>Wife, bring me forth the Pasty of Venison, and set me here my lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Table, that these Gentlemen may eat a bit with me before they go.</hi> His Wife, which had been often used to this term, excused the matter, saying: <hi>the little Table! good Lord Husband, I do wonder what you will do with the little Table now, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that is used already: I pray you good Husband content your self, and sit at the great Table this once.</hi> Then she whispered him in the ear, saying: <hi>What man, shall we shame our selves: What shame,</hi> quoth he? <hi>tell not me of shame, but do thou as thou art bidden: for we are three or four of us, then what do we trouble the great Table: Truly</hi> (answered she) <hi>the little Table is not ready now, good Husband let it alone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Trust me we are troublesome guests</hi> (said the <hi>Aldermen</hi>) <hi>but yet we would fain see your little Table because it is said to be of such a price. Yea, and it is my mind you shall,</hi> quoth Master <hi>Eyer, therefore he called his Wife again,</hi> saying: <hi>Good Wife, dispatch and prepare the little Table, for these Gentlemen would fain have a view of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereupon, his wife seeing him so earnest, according to her wonted manner, came in, and setting her self down on a low stool laid a fair Napkin over her knees, and set the Platter with the Pasty of <hi>Venison</hi> thereupon: and presently a Chair was brought for Master <hi>Alderman,</hi> &amp; a couple of low stools for the two Commoners, which they beholding, with a sudden and hearty Laughter, said: <hi>Why Master Sheriff, is this the Table you held so dear? Yes truly,</hi> quoth he: <hi>Now verily,</hi> (quoth they) <hi>you herein have utterly deceived our expectation. Even so did you mine,</hi> quoth he, <hi>in mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me Sheriff: but you are all right welcome: and I tell you true, had I not thought wondrous well of you, you had not seen my Table now. And I think did my Lord</hi> Mayor <hi>see it as you do, he would repent his bargain so hastily made. Notwithstanding, I account my Table never the worse: nor have you any cause</hi> (quoth they). And so af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter much pleasant talk they departed, spreading the fame of Master <hi>Sheriff,</hi> Table over the whole City.</p>
               <p>But you must now imagine that a thousand cares cumbred the Sheriff, in provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all things necessary for his Office: at what time he put off his Shoomakers shop to one of his men, and set up at the same time the sign of the <hi>Black-Swan swimm ng upon the Sea,</hi> in remembrance of that Ship that first did bring him his Wealth: and before that time the Sign of the <hi>Black Swan</hi> was never seen or known in any place in or about the City of <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV. How <hi>Haunce</hi> having circumvented <hi>Iohn</hi> the Frenchmans love, was by him and others finely deceived at the Garden.</head>
               <p>NOw at that time <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Frenchman</hi> and fair <hi>Florence</hi> were both at variance, as you heard before by the <hi>Dutchmans</hi> dealing, by which subtilty he sought means to win favour for himself, which <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Frenchman</hi> perceived, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore went about not only to prevent him, but to take revenge on him for his deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness: and meeting <hi>Florence</hi> as she went into the garden for Flowers, he began to talk thus unto her.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:99084:25"/>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <hi>What</hi> Florence, <hi>you go to the Garden? and how then,</hi> quoth she? <hi>what have you to say to that? Me sea nothing, but you be discontent: you no speak a me; you no look a me; nor you no drink with me, nor nothing: ah</hi> Florence, <hi>how chance dat?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Go get thee hence pratling fool,</hi> quoth she, <hi>I drink with thee, thou shall be Py-peckt first. Py-peckt! what be Py-peckt? a hea: Begot</hi> Florence, <hi>you make me a Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nape, you mock a me, and call be shitten</hi> Iohn, <hi>and you be so proud, because</hi> Haunce <hi>love you, dat shall be marvel: but and if you call me shitten</hi> Iohn <hi>any more, on my say shall not put up, shall not take at your hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who told you that I called you shitten</hi> Iohn (<hi>quoth</hi> Florence,) <hi>I never called you so. No</hi> Florence, <hi>you no call me a shitten</hi> Iohn, <hi>also me shant villain pulard</hi> Haunce <hi>tell ame so. I never said so, quoth</hi> Florence. <hi>But</hi> Haunce <hi>told me that you made your boast that I was at a beck of your finger: and that you could make me follow you up and down the whole City for a Pint of Wine. No, I would you should well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, I will not follow a better man than you. O, of my fet</hi> Florence, <hi>me never said so. No; yes,</hi> quoth she, <hi>but you did, I can tell you by a good token, for that very time that I should have met you at Islington you said it, and made me a fool to come over the fields to you; and when all came to all, you sent</hi> Haunce <hi>to tell, that you were gone there-hence long ago.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abcet token</hi> Haunce, quoth Iohn, <hi>bedes ten bon, 'tis true, for me tarry dere more den one, two, tree hour, and had provide shapon de rabit, de cream, de pudding-pye, and twenty dings more: well, howsoever it was, I am sure I was made an Ass betwixt you, and for that cause I will beware how I shew kindness again to any: therefore</hi> Iohn <hi>I pray you be gone, and seek some other company, for you shall not go with me. No, said</hi> Iohn: <hi>well den adieu</hi> Florence, <hi>and so they departed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now it is be be understood, that <hi>Haunce</hi> had promised <hi>Florence</hi> to meet her in the Garden, and to bring with him a bottle of Wine, and there in the presence of a Maid or two more, to make themselves sure together; and she for that purpose had carried with her the corner of a Venison Pasty. But there was an <hi>English</hi> Iourney-man in the house, called <hi>Nicholas,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>stood thereof, who meeting with <hi>John</hi> the French-men, he made him pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> thereunto, saying: <hi>Trust me</hi> Iohn, <hi>if thou wilt be ruled by me, we will not only disappoint this match, but also with their good chear make our selves merry:</hi> Iohn, who was glad and ready to do the Dutch-man an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, consented to follow <hi>Nicholas</hi> his counsel in any thing.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:99084:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then,</hi> quoth Nicholas, <hi>it shall be thus: I will go to the Garden, and stay for</hi> Haunce <hi>his coming with the Wine, and in the mean space do thou hide thy self under one of the hedges of the Garden on the other side, and with thee take a couple of Pots, and let the one be empty, and the other filled with water; and when</hi> Haunce <hi>is come into the Garden with his Bottle of Wine (now he will not let me see it by his good will, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding) I'le observe where he doth set it down, and then I will find the means, while they are busie in toying and talking, to convey the bottle of Wine through the hedge to thee, and likewise the Venison: then emptying the bottle, thou shalt fill it with water, and thrusting it through the hedge again, it shall be set where it first was found: which being done, thou shalt hastily rap at the door, at what time they shall be told that it is our Master or Mistriss; which they hearing, will be in such a maze, that on a sudden they will not know which way to turn themselves, especially for the conveying away of</hi> Haunce: <hi>Now when you have knockt twice or thrice, and that you hear no body come to the door, get you away, and stay for me at the</hi> Rose at Barking, <hi>and there we will drink up their Wine, and eat up their Venison: and this being done we will laugh them to scorn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Truly</hi> Nicholas, quoth Iohn <hi>the</hi> Frenchman, <hi>this will be brave:</hi> And thereupon they prepared themselves to do the feat. <hi>Nicholas</hi> therefore got him into the Garden, and by and by after comes <hi>Haunce</hi> with the bottle of Wine, who knocking at the Garden door was straight let in: but seeing <hi>Nicholas</hi> there, he secretly set his bottle in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but <hi>Nick</hi> who had as searching eyes as <hi>Argus</hi> in his business, quickly did as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had determined: <hi>and instead of Wine, set the bottle down again, where he had found it full of Water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then comes <hi>John</hi> and lustily knocks at the door: <hi>There is our Master and Mistriss,</hi> (quoth <hi>Nicholas</hi>) <hi>Alas</hi> quoth she, <hi>get you over the hedge. Shall I open the door?</hi> quoth <hi>Nick. O no,</hi> said <hi>Florence, not yet good Nick. With that he</hi> knockt more hastily: Anon, anon, quoth he. Hence <hi>Haunce:</hi> go to the door <hi>Nick. Who is there?</hi> quoth he, and with that opening the door, he found just no body. <hi>Truly Florence,</hi> said he, <hi>they are gone whosoever they were. God be with you, I can stay no longer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When he was departed, the Maids wished that <hi>Haunce</hi> had been there again. <hi>Alas, poor fellow,</hi> quoth they, <hi>he is gone and left his bottle behind him? Marry I am glad that it is no worse,</hi> quoth <hi>Florence: and now that the Wine is here, we will drink it for his sake, and I have here a morsel of Venison, that will give it a good relish:</hi> And therewithal looking for it, she found the cloath, but the meat was gone. <hi>Now a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on it,</hi> quoth she, <hi>one scurvy Cur or other hath got into the Garden and took away the meat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O God, what ill luck is that</hi> (quoth the Maid) <hi>a murren on that Cur that got it: but seeing it is gone, farewell it. Well,</hi> said <hi>Florence, here is the Wine yet, I know it is excellent good, for he told me he would bring a bottle of the best</hi> Rhenish <hi>Wine that could be bought in</hi> London, <hi>and I am certain he is as good as his word: But believe me</hi> Ione, <hi>he is kind hearted, and as loving a fellow as ever professed love to any. I assure you that here is a cup of Wine that the King may drink thereof: But how shall we do for a glass? weel drink it out of the bottle, said</hi> Ione. <hi>Not so,</hi> quoth Florence, <hi>I do love to see what I drink, and therefore I'le borrow a glass at the next house. And while she goes for a glass,</hi> said Ione to her self, <hi>I'le have a tast of it before she returns</hi> again: then seting her hand unto the bottle, and the bottle unto her mouth, she drank a good draught, and finding it be to be something thin in going down, she said to <hi>Bess</hi> that sat by, Credit me now, but for the name of Wine I have drank as good Water.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99084:26"/>
                  <hi>It is</hi> Rhenish-<hi>Wine,</hi> quoth <hi>Bess, and that is never strong. It may be made of Rain, well enough,</hi> quoth <hi>Jone. At which words Florence</hi> entred with a glass: and pouring it out into a glass, she extolled the colour, saying: <hi>See what a brave colour it hath? it is as clear, I do assure you, as the Rock-Water:</hi> and there-withal drinking it off, she said, <hi>It drinks very dead: Of a truth,</hi> quoth she, <hi>this is but bad Wine, it is even as dead as a door nail:</hi> And so filling the glass again she gave it unto <hi>Bess,</hi> she tasting thereof, said: <hi>Passion of me, this is plain Water. Water,</hi> said <hi>Jone, Is it Water? Let me taste it once again, by my Maiden-head it is Water indeed</hi> quoth she. <hi>Water,</hi> said Florence, <hi>you have plaid the Drabs in drinking out the Wine, and filled the Bottle again with Water. Of my faith,</hi> quoth Ione, <hi>you say not true in so saying: I would you did understand, we played not the Drabs in any such sort, but</hi> Haunce <hi>rather played the Knave, that brought us water instead of Wine. Nay,</hi> quoth Florence, <hi>I dare swear for him, that he would not serve you so for all the wealth my Master is worth: And I am perswaded, that it was no body but your selves that did it: But in faith, you might have dealt so with another, and not with me. Nay then</hi> (quoth they) <hi>you need not serve us so, to cause us to drink Water instead of Wine: and we would you should think, although you be Master</hi> Sheriffs <hi>Maid, we do love our mouths as well as you do yours for your life, and it was but a homely recompence for our good will, I tell you true, neither do we care how lit le we come to be thus deluded. Go to, go to,</hi> said Florence, <hi>you are like to</hi> Penelope's <hi>Puppy, that doth both bite and whine: I know you well enough. Know us</hi> (quoth <hi>Jone</hi>) <hi>What do you know by us? We defie you for any thing you can say by us. Know us; Nay, it were well if thou didst know thy self: and hearest thou, though thou hast thy companions to meet thee at thy pleasure, and we have not: No, know us: We are known to be as honest as thou art, or else we should be sorry:</hi> And so they departed in a chafe.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>John</hi> the Frenchman, and <hi>Nicholas,</hi> having eaten the Venison, and drunk up the Wine, came back again time enough to hear all this strife, whereat they greatly rejoyced: but so soon as <hi>Florence</hi> did meet with <hi>Haunce</hi> again, she kept no small stir for mocking her with a bottle of Water, about the which they fell at variances, in such sort that they were not friends for a long time after.</p>
               <p>But during the time that <hi>Haunce</hi> was out of favour, <hi>Nicholas</hi> sought the Maids friendship by all the means he might, but in vain was his pains spent therein: for although <hi>Florence</hi> outwardly seemed much displeased, yet <hi>Haunce</hi> had her Heart still, and in process of time obtained great favour the matter was grown so forward, that the perform once of their Marriage was forthwith appointed, which they intended should be celebrated at the Abby of <hi>Grace</hi> on <hi>Tower-hill.</hi> Notwithstanding, this matter was not kept so close, but that their secret dealings were known, and <hi>Nicholas</hi> purposing to deceive the <hi>Dutchman,</hi> made <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Frenchman</hi> privy thereunto, saying: <hi>John, it is so, that this night at midnight Mass</hi> Florence <hi>and</hi> Haunce <hi>do intend secretly to be Married, and they have appointed the Fryer to do it as soon as the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers are all put out, because they will not be seen of any: therefore</hi> Iohn <hi>if now you will be my friend, I doubt not but to marry her my self, and so to give the</hi> Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>the Slampam, and bore him through the nose with a cushion. Ha</hi> (<abbr>qd</abbr>
                  <hi>John</hi>) <hi>be Got me shall do as you sea: and therefore</hi> Nicholas <hi>tell me what you do? Marry</hi> Iohn, <abbr>qd</abbr> he, <hi>you know the Dutchman loveth to drink well, and by that he loveth, weel cause him to lose his love: for we will get him out to the Tavern, and there cause him to be disguised, that he shall</hi> be neither able to stand or go. <hi>John</hi> the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99084:27"/>
                  <hi>French-man hearing this, scratching his head, and rubbing his elbow, said: Masoy,</hi> Nicholas, <hi>dis be the Fine tricks, how shall we get him forth a doors. Excellent well,</hi> quoth Nicholas, <hi>for there is a new Journey-man come to Town with St.</hi> Hugh's <hi>bones at his back, and you know that he being of the Gentle-Craft, must go to give him his welcome; and I will tell</hi> Haunce <hi>thereof, who being now very jocund, by reason that his Marriage is so near, will not deny to come I know. Therefore you and the strange Journey-man shall go before to the Tavern, and then I will go fetch him. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beene, content, content, said</hi> Iohn.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And so to the Tavern he hasted with the strange man. Anon comes</hi> Nicholas <hi>and</hi> Haunce, <hi>and with them two or three Journey-men more, and all to the new Journey-man:</hi> sitting down they got <hi>Haunce</hi> in the midst, <hi>called for wine lustily, and such varieties, as the Dutchman was soon set packing: for every one sought to over-charge him; and being himself of a good kind to take his liquor, spared not to pledge eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man. At what time, in the midst of his Cups, being well whitled, his tongue ran at random (as Wine is the bewrayer of secrets) so it proved by him, for there he opened to his companions all his mind, saying: My hearts, for all I sit here, I must be a married man ere the morning. God give you joy</hi> (quoth they) <hi>but who shall you marry, said</hi> Nick: Florence? <hi>Yea,</hi> Florence, <hi>said the</hi> Dutchman, <hi>that is the Lass that I do love, and all the world cannot deceive me of her now, I am the man that must have her Maiden-head, and this night we must be married at the</hi> Abby <hi>of</hi> Grace, <hi>and if you be good fellows, go with me to Church: will you go with me? will we gad with thee</hi> (said <hi>John</hi> the French-man) <hi>that we will. O</hi> Iohn (said <hi>Haunce</hi>) <hi>I have wiped your nose and</hi> Nicks <hi>too, you must wear the Willow Garland. Well, what remedy</hi> (quoth they) <hi>it is the better for you: But in faith</hi> Haunce, <hi>seeing it is so,</hi> (quoth <hi>Nick</hi>) <hi>we'l have one pottle of Wine more, that we may drink to the health of your Bride. I'le pledge her if it be a gallon</hi> (quoth <hi>Haunce</hi>). <hi>By my fet and trot, said</hi> Iohn, <hi>will have a gallon: be a Drawer, where be you: I pray you bring me a gallon of de best Claret, and a gallon of de best Sack; shall make merry I fet: What!</hi> Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <hi>be Marry and I no know: But by this time that this Wine was drank,</hi> Haunce <hi>was laid up for walking any more that night. When</hi> Nick <hi>perceived that, he stole sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly out of the Tavern, and went to meet</hi> Florence <hi>at the appointed place: but</hi> Iohn <hi>quickly missing him, knew straight whereabout he went, &amp; got him presently to the Constable of the Postern-Gate, and told him,</hi> that <hi>Nick</hi> had laid a man for dead in Tower-street, &amp; that he was gone to save himself under the Priviledge of the Abby of <hi>Grace? But,</hi> quoth he, <hi>if you will go along, I shall bring him out with fair words unto you, and then I desire you to clap him up to answer this matter in the morning. But where dwell you!</hi> said the Constable? <hi>I do dwell with Master Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Eyer (quoth <hi>John</hi>) <hi>and there you shall have me at all times.</hi> The Constable did as <hi>John</hi> bad him, &amp; committed <hi>Nicholas</hi> to Prison. In the mean space, <hi>Florence,</hi> &amp; an old woman of Tower-street, said: <hi>they did go to a Womans labour,</hi> &amp; by that means they passed along by the Watch, and to the <hi>Abby</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> they came: they had not long been there, but that <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Frenchman</hi> meeting them, said: <hi>Florence, Well met, here is a fit place to finish that I have long looked for: John</hi> (quoth she) <hi>thou art like an evil Spirit, that must be conjured out, before a body shall get any q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etness: urge not me upon any such matters, for you be not the man I look for: and therefore, taking as little pleasure in your presence, as of your proffers, I would be very glad to see your back. What</hi> said <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn,</hi> have you no compassion on a poor man: you are hard hearted indeed. But as he was uttering these speeches, it was his Wives chance to bear his tongue, being newly come from the Barge at Billing-sgate,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99084:27"/> and at that time going towards St. <hi>Katharines,</hi> to see if she could meet with some of her Country-folks that could tell her any tydings of her Husband; but as I said, hearing his tongue, and knowing him by his speech, she said: What▪ <hi>John Dene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vale! My Husband,</hi> Iohn Denevale, <hi>what make you wed pretty wench? hea:</hi> At these words, <hi>John</hi> was stricken into such a dumb, that he wist not what to say: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, hearing <hi>Florence</hi> to ask if she was his Wife, he answered, and said, <hi>Yea. O thou dissembling fellow!</hi> quoth she, <hi>is it even so? didst thou not say thou wast a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelor; seeking to marry me, and hast a Wife alive? Now fie on thee: O good Lord! how was I blest to escape him! Nay, now I see that</hi> Haunce <hi>may have a Wife in</hi> Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>too, although he be here! and therefore by the grace of God I will not marry a stranger. O, quoth</hi> Iohn! <hi>I thought my Wife had been dead, but seeing she is alive, I will not lose her for twenty thousand Crowns.</hi> So <hi>Florence</hi> departed, and left <hi>John</hi> with his Wife.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Haunce</hi> never waking until it was next day at noon, when he saw he had overslept himself, being very sorry, he went home, not knowing how to excuse his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Florence,</hi> whom she now utterly forsook, as well in regard of his drunkenness, as for that being a stranger, he might (like <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Frenchman</hi> have another Wife living. But <hi>Nicholas</hi> (that all this while lay in Prison) being brought before Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman <hi>Eyer,</hi> rehearsed the Truth, and craving pardon for his Offence, was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any more ado delivered: And <hi>Florence</hi> being called before him, he made up the match between her and his Man <hi>Nicholas,</hi> marrying them out of his own house with credit, giving them a good stock to begin the World withal: also for <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Frenchman</hi> did very much: and shewed himself a good Master to his Man <hi>Haunce,</hi> and to all the rest of his Servants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CAHP. XV. How Master Alderman <hi>Eyer</hi> was chosen Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> and how he feasted the Apprentices on Shrove-tuesday.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>WIthin a few years after, Alderman <hi>Eyer</hi> being chosen Lord Mayor of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> changing his Copy, he became one of the Worshipful company of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and for this year be kept a most bountiful house. At this time it came into his mind what a promise once he made to the Prentices, being at breakfast with them at their going to the Conduit, speaking to his Lady in this wise: <hi>Good Lord</hi> (quoth he) <hi>what a change have we had within these thirty years? and how greatly hath the Lord blessed us since that! blessed be his Name for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:99084:28"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>I do remember when I was a young Prentice, what a match I did make upon a</hi> Shrovetuesday <hi>Morning, being at the Conduit among other of my Companions: trust me Wife</hi> (quoth he) <hi>it is worth the hearing, and I'le tell thee how it fell out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>After we had filled our Tankards with Water, there was some would needs have me set down my Tankard, and go with them to Breakfast (as many times before I had done) to which I consented, and it was to a breakfast of Pudding-Pies, I shall never forget it: but to make short, when the shot came to be paid, each one drew out his money, but I had not one penny in my Purse, and credit I had none in the place; which when I beheld, being ashamed, I said, Well my Masters, do you give me my Breakfast this time, and in requital thereof, if ever I be Lord Mayor of</hi> London, <hi>I'le bestow a Breakfast on all the Prentices of the City: These were the words, little thinking</hi> (God wot) <hi>that ever it should come to pass: but such was the great goodness of our God, who setteth up the humble, and pulleth down the proud, to bring whom he pleaseth to the seat of Honour: For as the Scripture wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesseth, Promotion cometh neither from the East, nor from the West, but from him who is the giver of all good things, the mighty Lord of Heaven and Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore Wife, seeing God hath bestowed that upon me, that I never looked for, it is reason that I should perform my promise, and being able now I'le pay that which then I was not able to do: for I would not have men say, that I am like the Ebon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, that neither bears Leaves nor Fruit. Wherefore Wife, seeing that</hi> Shrove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuesday <hi>is so near at hand, I will upon that day fulfil my promise which upon that day I made. Truly My Lord,</hi> (quoth she) <hi>I will be right willing thereunto. Then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered my Lord, as thou dost love me, let them want neither Pudding-Pies nor Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cakes; and look what other good chear is to be had, I will refer all to your discretion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon great provision was made for the Prentices breakfast: and <hi>Shrove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuesday</hi> being come, the Lord Mayor sent word to the Aldermen, that in their several Wards they should signifie his mind to the Citizens, to crave their favours that their Prentices might come to his house to Breakfast, and that for his sake they might play all the day after.</p>
               <p>Hereupon it was ordered, that at the ringing of a Bell in every Parish, the Pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices should leave work, and shut up their shops for that day; which being ever since yearly observed, is called the Pancake Bell. The Prentices being all assembled, my Lord Mayors house was not able to hold them, they were such a multitude: so that besides the great Hall, all the Gardens were set with Tables, and in the Backside Tables were set, and every other place was also furnished, so that at length they were all placed: and while meat was bringing in, to delight their ears, as well as to feed their bodies, and to drown the noise of their Pratlings, Drums and Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets were pleasantly sounded: that being ended, the Waits of the City, with divers other sorts of Musick, played also to beguile the time, and to put off all dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content.</p>
               <p>After the first service, were all the Tables plentifully furnished with Pudding pies and Pancakes in very plentiful manner; and the rest that remained was given to the poor; Wine &amp; Ale in very great measure they had given, insomuch that they had no lack nor excess to cause them to be disordered And in the midst of this their mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, the Lord Mayor in his Scarlet Gown, and his Lady in like manner, went in amongst them, bidding them all heartily Welcome: saying unto them. That his promise so long ago made, he hath at length performed. At what time they in token of thankfulness flung up their Caps, giving a great shout, and in continently they all quietly departed.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:99084:28"/>
               <p>Then after this Sir <hi>Simon Eyer</hi> builded <hi>Leaden-Hall,</hi> appointing that in the mid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> thereof there should be a Market-place kept every Munday for Leather, where the Shoomakers of <hi>London,</hi> for their more ease, might buy of the Tanners with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out seeking any further. And in the end this worthy man ended his life in <hi>London</hi> with great honour.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poems">
            <div type="sonnet">
               <head>A New Love-Sonnet.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>ALL hail sweet youth, fair Venus graft,</l>
                     <l>Chief Master of the Gentle-Craft;</l>
                     <l>How Comely seem'st thou in my sight?</l>
                     <l>Like Phebus in the Heavens bright;</l>
                     <l>That never was in Cupid's pound,</l>
                     <l>Or from his Shaft receiv'd a wound:</l>
                     <l>Thy mind with mirth it doth appear,</l>
                     <l>And so thy Love is free from grief &amp; eare.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Shoomakers.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Fair Maid you speak no more but truth:</l>
                     <l>For why, the freedom of my youth,</l>
                     <l>I value at too high a rare,</l>
                     <l>To link my self with any mate;</l>
                     <l>There is no comfort on the earth,</l>
                     <l>Compared to a free born mirth:</l>
                     <l>When fairest beauties me ore-thwart,</l>
                     <l>I look the better to my heart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When beautous Nymphs do me Surprize,</l>
                     <l>I shut the Casements of my eyes,</l>
                     <l>For he is a fond and foolish Else,</l>
                     <l>That loves a Maid, losing himself:</l>
                     <l>To fall in love is such a thing,</l>
                     <l>From whence sometimes doth mischief spring;</l>
                     <l>I wish well unto women-kind,</l>
                     <l>But for to wed I have no mind.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What if your Casements chance to ope,</l>
                     <l>And give affection so much scope,</l>
                     <l>As to encounter with a Dame:</l>
                     <l>Why then methinks it were a shame</l>
                     <l>For you to love and noc to speak,</l>
                     <l>And by degrees the Ice to break,</l>
                     <l>But if you speak and so obtain,</l>
                     <l>Then have you found your heart again.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It were a shame for Maids to wooe;</l>
                     <l>But men may speak, and so may you,</l>
                     <l>If that occasion offered be,</l>
                     <l>God Cupid's blind and cannot see,</l>
                     <l>But shoots at random here and there,</l>
                     <l>O therefore <hi>Comund</hi> have a care,</l>
                     <l>At unawares you may be hit,</l>
                     <l>No Policy can hinder it.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But, O unhappy women kind;</l>
                     <l>That toxicated are in mind,</l>
                     <l>And know not how to vent the same,</l>
                     <l>Without the loss of our good name:</l>
                     <l>They count us bold if now and than</l>
                     <l>We do but look upon a man;</l>
                     <l>And look we may, but dare not speak,</l>
                     <l>Much less our mind unto them break.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Shoomaker.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Would I were worthy for to know</l>
                     <l>The cause of this your grief and woe;</l>
                     <l>For why? your words and looks declare</l>
                     <l>Your mind is over-charg'd with care;</l>
                     <l>If that your heart be fled away,</l>
                     <l>And it be taken for a stray,</l>
                     <l>The Man that hath it, I'le perswade</l>
                     <l>To take some pity on a Maid.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This Young man struck this fair Maid mute;</l>
                     <l>She wanted one to plead her suit.</l>
                     <l>Fain would she speak but was afraid,</l>
                     <l>This is the case of many a Maid;</l>
                     <l>He was the man whom she lov'd best,</l>
                     <l>Her Heart did lodge within his Breast,</l>
                     <l>Although to him it was unknown,</l>
                     <l>Until at last he lost his own.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Cupid the God of Love came down,</l>
                     <l>And on this Young Man cast a frown,</l>
                     <l>He bent his bow, and sent a dart,</l>
                     <l>That struck the Young man to the Heart,</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:99084:29"/>
                     <l>And cause the Maid should win the prize,</l>
                     <l>He open'd the Shoomakers eyes:</l>
                     <l>So when her beauty he beheld,</l>
                     <l>He gladly yielded up the field.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>With folded arms along he walkt.</l>
                     <l>And thus unto himself he talkt,</l>
                     <l>O what are we that vainly trust,</l>
                     <l>In our weak strengths that are but dust:</l>
                     <l>I dust have sworn no living wight,</l>
                     <l>Could move me from my sweet delight:</l>
                     <l>But now <hi>I</hi> see and feel the smart,</l>
                     <l>Mine eyes to soon deceive my heart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He that before was grown so stout,</l>
                     <l>And strong enough to keep love out,</l>
                     <l>Is vanquisht now made to yield,</l>
                     <l>And did both win and lose the field:</l>
                     <l>He conquered her to him unknown.</l>
                     <l>She conquered him, made him her own:</l>
                     <l>Thus Maids with Men are dallying still,</l>
                     <l>Till they have brought them to their will.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Alas, quoth he, how am I crost,</l>
                     <l>Beholding her my self I have lost:</l>
                     <l>Now beauty is become a snare,</l>
                     <l>The which hath brought me to despair:</l>
                     <l>If she no other man had lov'd,</l>
                     <l>I might have hope she might be mov'd,</l>
                     <l>But she another doth affect,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>I</hi> must dye without respect.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>She noting of his passion then,</l>
                     <l>As Maids well do that love Young-men,</l>
                     <l>And finding the occasion fit,</l>
                     <l>Mark here a wily wenches wit:</l>
                     <l>Delays prove dangerous she knew,</l>
                     <l>And many Maids have found it true:</l>
                     <l>Thus in her self resolv'd to speak,</l>
                     <l>She unto him her mind did break.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Quoth she, Young man it is your lot,</l>
                     <l>The God of love hath laid a plot,</l>
                     <l>The Net is spread, the Bird is caught,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>I</hi> have found the thing <hi>I</hi> sought:</l>
                     <l>Though men are strong an Women weak,</l>
                     <l>Stout hearts will yield before they'l break,</l>
                     <l>And Women sometimes win the field,</l>
                     <l>When men are willing for to yield.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>With that the Nymphs and Rural Swains,</l>
                     <l>Came strait way tripping or'e the plains;</l>
                     <l>The Satyrs made them Pipes of Reeds,</l>
                     <l>And brought in Musick more than needs:</l>
                     <l>The Syrens sung such songs of mirth,</l>
                     <l>That brought King <hi>Obeon</hi> from th'earth:</l>
                     <l>The Faries with the Fairy King,</l>
                     <l>Did dance about them in a Ring.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All health and happiness betide,</l>
                     <l>The Shoomaker and his sweet Bride,</l>
                     <l>Lo thus we sing, and thus we dance,</l>
                     <l>Till we have brought love in a trance:</l>
                     <l>Thus pleasures sweet these couple grace,</l>
                     <l>Both link'd together in a sweet imbrace,</l>
                     <l>The neighbbouring Hills and Dales rebound</l>
                     <l>With eccho of our pleasant sound.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whilst thus they sung their round-delays</l>
                     <l>God Cupid crown'd their heads with bays</l>
                     <l>The Bride look like the Queen of <hi>May,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Shoomaker led her away:</l>
                     <l>Where now they live in quiet peace,</l>
                     <l>And love doth more and more increase,</l>
                     <l>Thus love you see can find a way,</l>
                     <l>To make both Men and Maids obey,</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:99084:29"/>
               <head>How a Shoomakers Widow fell in love with her Man.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>These three years <hi>Iohn,</hi> I have been deep in Love,</l>
                  <l>And ne'r till now had time my mind to move;</l>
                  <l>Speak, canst thou love me, though I am thy Dame?</l>
                  <l>I would not have thee daunted; Fie for shame:</l>
                  <l>Old Proverb, <hi>Spare to speak, and spare to speed.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou want'st a Wife, and <hi>I</hi> a Husband need.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>His Answer.</head>
                  <l>Mistriss, <hi>I</hi> am in Love as well 'tis true,</l>
                  <l>But to speak truth, in truth I love not you:</l>
                  <l>I have a Maid in chase, as sweet a Lass,</l>
                  <l>In my conceit, I think, as ever was:</l>
                  <l>Pray then forbear, it never shall be said,</l>
                  <l>I took a Widow and forsook a Maid.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="distich">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Reader, Observe what's written by the Poet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Women and Maids love Men, but few shew it.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>